<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sidrophel vapulans, or, The quack-astrologer toss'd in a blanket by the author of Medicaster medicatus ; in an epistle to W---m S---n [i.e. William Salmon] ; with a postscript, reflecting briefly on his late scurilous libel against the Royal College of Physicians, entituled, A rebuke to the authors of the blue book, by the same hand.</title>
            <author>Yonge, James, 1647-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y42A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32944</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12793615</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12793615</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93964</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67813)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93964)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1538:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sidrophel vapulans, or, The quack-astrologer toss'd in a blanket by the author of Medicaster medicatus ; in an epistle to W---m S---n [i.e. William Salmon] ; with a postscript, reflecting briefly on his late scurilous libel against the Royal College of Physicians, entituled, A rebuke to the authors of the blue book, by the same hand.</title>
                  <author>Yonge, James, 1647-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 59 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and sold by John Nutt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [16]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salmon, William, 1644-1713. --  A rebuke to the authors of a blew-book, call'd The state of physic in London.</term>
               <term>Royal College of Physicians of London.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93964:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93964:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SIDROPHEL VAP<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LANS:</hi> OR, THE <hi>Quack-Aſtrologer</hi> Toſs'd in a BLANKET.</p>
            <p>By the AUTHOR of <hi>Medicaſter Medicatus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In an Epiſtle to <hi>W—m S—n.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> Reflecting briefly on his late Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous Libel againſt the <hi>Royal College of Phyſicians,</hi> Entituled, <hi>A Rebuke to the Authors of a Blue Book.</hi> By the ſame Hand.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Aſtrologi! Genus hominum potentibus infidum, ſperantibus fallax,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Tacit. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>By theſe Fables</hi> Aſtrologers Live, Cheat, <hi>and</hi> Get Money. <hi>Indeed no Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Men are more Pernicious to a Commonwealth,</hi> C. Agrippa.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are more</hi> Empirical Impoſtors, <hi>more</hi> Idiots, Illiterate Cheats, <hi>pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to</hi> Aſtrology <hi>in this your</hi> Royal City, <hi>than of any other ſort, not only</hi> Seducing, <hi>but</hi> Ruining <hi>many of your Majeſty's poor Subjects. Dr.</hi> Ramſey<hi>'s</hi> Ded. <hi>of his</hi> Tract. de Ven. 1661.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>John Nutt,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93964:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93964:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable and Learned <hi>COL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEGE of PHYSICIANS,</hi> and Worſhipful <hi>SOCIETY of SURGEONS,</hi> London.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Learned and Wortly Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HEalth is not only the Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and Intereſt of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry individual Man in a Body Politick; but of the whole Community; becauſe Diſeaſes and Hurts (by diſabling Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſons from Publick Service) do weaken and infeeble the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>It's therefore a great wonder, that in this Age of Regulation and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, nothing is done to recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the notorious Abuſes, and ſecure us from the Miſchief done by thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:93964:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Men; who (without Skill or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) under pretence of reſtoring and conſerving, do deſtroy Mens Lives and Eſtates; and more eſpecially at ſuch a time when the Nation is in need of both, for its Defence and Preſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reformation</hi> is a Name we are very fond of, and a Work we ſeem to be alway doing: But when will it be done? We have lately gained a new Law to ſecure <hi>Apothecaries</hi> from being Scavengers; Is there not more need of one to keep <hi>Shooemakers</hi> from turning <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Moon-Prophets? What elſe means the bleating of thoſe Sheep in our Ears?</hi> If the Body Politick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of many Natural ones, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the one, is the Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the other; and that's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond a <hi>Cobler</hi>'s <hi>Laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93964:3"/>
            <p>Why then ſhould Impudent, Ignorant <hi>Quacks</hi> and Empiricks (<q>Smiths, Weavers,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c. 11.</note> Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Draymen, Women) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> boldly and accuſtomably take upon them great Cures, and Things of great Difficulty? In the which, thy partly uſe Sorcery and Witchcraft, partly apply ſuch Medicines unto the Diſeaſe, as be very noyous and nothing meet therefore; to the high Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of God, great Infamy to the Faculty, and the grievous Hurt, Damage and Deſtruction of many of the King's Liege People; moſt eſpecially of them that cannot diſcern the uncunning from the cunning.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Declaration by a <hi>Statute Law</hi> of this Nation, theſe Impoſtors, as if they were Paramount to all Law, Superior to the Supreme; or Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants <hi>cum Privilegio,</hi> do with Impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Defraud Men, not only of Health and Wealth, but Limb and Life too: And this, not only in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb facs="tcp:93964:4"/>but in our <hi>Metropolis,</hi> in the Face of the Government, and of You, whoſe Province it is (if any Bodies) to Suppreſs ſuch Pernicious and Deſtructive Vermin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> It plainly appears by Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Statute. Laws of the Kingdom, and the Royal Grants of Kings and Queens of <hi>England,</hi> that you do not want ſufficient Authority for this Good Work; and I am ſure you cannot want Skill and Learning e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to Alarm the Nation againſt them, to Baffle and Expoſe them to the World in their true Colours, that People may ſee in what Hands they truſt their Lives.</p>
            <p>It's your Duty and your Intereſt ſo to do. It's a Noble Work to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move thoſe Nuiſances; though the Subject of your Cenſure be vile as the Perſon is, whom I have now in
<pb facs="tcp:93964:4"/>hand, yet the Undertaking is Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and worthy of <hi>You. Hercules</hi> thought it a beſitting Labour to cleanſe <hi>Augeas</hi>'s Stables. Juſtice is not diſparaged by Sentencing the vileſt Malefactor to the Gallows. The Good atchieved to the Publick by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Act, hallows it. And thus may preſent Undertaking becomes worthy of your Patronage, and Imitation; and I preſume to crave both.</p>
            <p>For, beſide the Common Injury <hi>Empiricks</hi> do to Mankind in general, they have a particular ſpight againſt you, which they ſpare not to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver on all occaſions. <hi>Culpeper</hi> in one Breath Sentenced a whole <hi>College</hi> of your moſt Learned Predeceſſors, and King <hi>James</hi> their Patron, to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. And this his <hi>Zany</hi> not only commends, but imitates him; affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting you to the <hi>Queen,</hi> in a Dedication
<pb facs="tcp:93964:5"/>of that Book wherein he abuſeth me to the Reader, and in many other Rude Libels. I am therefore obliged to him, for giving me ſuch good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and ſhall be quit with him anon.</p>
            <p>He hath indeed a peculiar Merit in him which ought to be regarded: he is an <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> as well as an <hi>Empirick;</hi> and that's a Compoſition, which Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons both Body and Soul; cheats Men not only of their Money and Health, but of their Loyalty too; whereby he becomes obnoxious to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment more ways than one; and ought to be Chaſtiſed by them with a Whip in the Houſe of Correction, as well as by us in the Preſs.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Aſtrological Quacks</hi> do not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reproach, Libel and Rail at you, but Uſurp your Office, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <hi>Law;</hi> taking upon them to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb facs="tcp:93964:5"/>the Settled Rules, Methods, and Medicaments, and give Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to all ſorts of <hi>Empiricks,</hi> and <hi>Quack-ſalvers.</hi> So that the <hi>Faculty</hi> is in danger of being overthrown, and the Nation ſubjected to all thoſe inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, which the want of Able Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, and the multiplying Cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> can introduce.</p>
            <p>I know what I am to expect from theſe Men for giving them this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance; it's like ſtirring a Neſt of Waſps; and accordingly I expect all the <hi>Mountebanks</hi> and <hi>Astrologers</hi> in the Nation will fall on me: for they, like <hi>Swine,</hi> if you take one by the Ears, the whole Herd will ſqueal, and gruntle at him who doth it. He that toſſeth a Whelp in a Blanket, muſt expect much noiſe, and a filthy ſtink. And of this I am the more aſſured, becauſe the fear of it only,
<pb facs="tcp:93964:6"/>hath made this <hi>Hocus</hi> extract the Quinteſcence, or <hi>Powers</hi> of <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> and <hi>Bedlam,</hi> and throw it in my Face.</p>
            <p>But theſe Foreſights do not diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, nor damp me at all. If I ſerve Truth and the Publick, I gain my Point, let the <hi>Quacks</hi> and <hi>Astrological Impostors</hi> Rail on, and fling Dirt as faſt as they can. If I but continue in the Favour and Reputation I am Honour'd with by you, none of it will ſtick upon</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble Servant, <hi>James Younge.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93964:6"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>YOU cannot but think me induced by ſome ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry extraordinary Motive, to ſo mean an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, as that of Cenſuring an Author ſo Futile; and a Book ſo Contemptible, as an <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> and his <hi>Almanack.</hi> But no meanneſs of Perſon or Book, ought to exempt him or them from Chaſtiſement, when faulty. And that he whom I have taken to task, is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch, will appear in the following <hi>Examen;</hi> where, beſide the Miſchief this ſort of Men do the Nation in general, you will ſee the wrong this <hi>Mopus</hi> hath done me in particular, and that is Provocation enough to Chaſtiſe him.</p>
            <p>Some Years ago, he told the <hi>Mobb</hi> (few elſe read or regard his <hi>Gallymawfry</hi>) that I ſtole my Notions of <hi>Ol. Tereb.</hi> from <hi>Crato,</hi> an Author who hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in him which could colour ſo unjust and falſe a Reflection. And although he knew it to be ſo, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed either to confeſs it, or give ſatisfaction for the wrong he had done me: But fearing I would reſent it, and expoſe him, he in his next Libel falls a Railing at me, in a ſort moſt Rude and Senſeleſs, without one
<pb facs="tcp:93964:7"/>Reaſon to ſupport his ill Language; and repeats the ſame again in another Years <hi>Hodge-Podge,</hi> where he hath the Forehead to Publiſh the ſame Falſhood of <hi>Crato</hi> and Me, which he had done ſo many Years before. Theſe repeated Provocations conquered all the Reaſons which reſtrained my Pen from taking Satisfaction, and let it looſe upon him, with all its Reſentments of the Man, and the Trade he Practiſeth.</p>
            <p>Beſide thoſe particular Injuries this Lunatick hath done me, you will be far from thinking it an Idle or Impertinent Work, to Correct and Expoſe the whole Herd of thoſe noxious Creatures; if you conſider, that though they be Things hated by the Wiſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed by the Learned, they are not ſeldom cheriſh'd and employ'd by thoſe who Plot and Deſign to diſturb the Common Reſpoſe; and by ſuch have been made uſe of in all Ages, to ſeduce the Vulgar into Faction, and prejudice their Minds againſt Eſtabliſh'd Government. Inſtances of it are innumerable in the Story of all Times and Nations. And for it We are told by <hi>Tacitus, Pliny, Agrippa,</hi> and many others, they were often baniſhed <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> by the Decrees of ſeveral Senates, and Laws of divers Emperors; and that <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the famous Legiſlator, made it a Crime Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital. <hi>To the Commonwealth and Publick Peace</hi> (ſaith <hi>C. Agrippa,</hi> who was a great Lawyer, Stateſman and Aſtrologer) <hi>they have been perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in all Ages. For beſide their Frauds and
<pb facs="tcp:93964:7"/>Cozening Practices on the Common People, they are Authors of much Miſchief to a State, drawing Credulous People to their Ruine, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Wars and Sedition. No Sort or Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Men being more pernicious to a</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, <hi>than thoſe who undertake to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſticate by the Stars, and ſcatter their Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies about.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's no new thing to have Faction and Rebellion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted in this Nation by ſuch Men;<note place="margin">33 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.8.14.5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 15.23 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2.</note> and for that Reaſon-many Laws were made against them by our Wiſe Anceſtors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. Lilly</hi> and <hi>N. Culpeper</hi> are the laſt dead Instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it: And there are a couple of the ſame Stamp left alive to carry on the ſame Deſign, by the ſame Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin.</hi> l. 13. c. 1. <hi>P. Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> l. 4. c. 126.</note> Our Nation was long ſince famous among Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners for being deluded by Prophecies and addicted to Magick. And I would fain take off the Scandal, by expoſing thoſe who continue to maintain that Trade among us.</p>
            <p>He whom I have ſingled out for that purpoſe, ſeems to be the fatteſt of the Herd; and to have many additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Aggravations above <hi>ordinary Aſtrologers.</hi> There's a peculiar danger in him to the Government, manifeſt every Year, by his fond inculcating a lewd Prophecy, like that which the Arch-Impoſtor <hi>W. Lilly</hi> long ſince publiſhed againſt Monarchy, Predicting its final Down-fall, together with the Mitre and Coronet;
<pb facs="tcp:93964:8"/>and the eſtabliſhing of Democracy in <hi>England.</hi> This is the plain meaning, and most manifeſt deſign of it, manger the ſham Interpretation he hath lately put upon it,<note place="margin">See <hi>Baker</hi>'s Chron. p. 310 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 15.12 <hi>Car.</hi> 2.30.</note> for that's plainly forced and contrived, after I had threatened him with two Statutes, one againſt Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing Prophecies, foretelling a Change of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; another enjoyning the Obſervation of <hi>January</hi> the 30th, of which till then he took no notice, although he forgot not to Calendar his own Nativity; as his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>P</hi>— doth the Whipping of <hi>T. O.</hi> And both the <hi>Martyrdom</hi> of K. <hi>Charles,</hi> or elſe ſhun and affront it.</p>
            <p>Theſe things do more Miſchief among the Vulgar, than <hi>Milton, Cook, Goodwin, Ludlow,</hi> or all the odious Vindicators of Rebellion, Patricide, and Democracy, this laſt Age hath been plagued with. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manacks</hi> are Oracles to the Vulgar, and when larded, or rather baited to hook in Customers with fine Receipts, <hi>to cure even incurable Diſeaſes,</hi> become very Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and regarded mostly by ſuch as are leaſt able to penetrate into the Deluſion, or diſcern the Snare. Thus <hi>Lilly</hi> and <hi>Culpeper</hi> poyſoned the People formerly;<note place="margin">Mon. <hi>or no</hi> Mon. Cataſt. Magn.</note> and thus their Succeſſors carry on the ſame Deſign now. The laboured Diſcourſes of the Grand <hi>Boutefeus</hi> ſcarce reach the Hand, ſeldom the Underſtanding of the Populace; and are conſequently unable to do that Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, by Seducing and Diſaffecting them, as ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious <hi>Hieroglyphicks,</hi> and Prophetick Emblems of the
<pb facs="tcp:93964:8"/>Determination of <hi>Monarchy, Epiſcopacy,</hi> and <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility,</hi> and ſetting up <hi>Democracy</hi> in theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            <p>For thoſe Reaſons I have taken upon me to Laſh and Expoſe thoſe Men, and the Art by which they poyſon the Minds of People, and Conjure them out of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Allegiance. And if thoſe Incorrigible <hi>Figure-Caſters</hi> perſist in the Trade of Publiſhing ſuch Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Almanacks; I hope all good Subjects will be forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied againſt the Infection, Deſign, and Factious ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of them.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Moon-Prophet</hi> ſo exactly reſembles <hi>Sidro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> in <hi>Hudibraſs,</hi> that I choſe to treat him under that Character. How it fits, ſuch as know him may judge by the following Deſcription of his <hi>Prototype.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>He deals in <hi>Deſtinies</hi> dark Counſels,<note place="margin">Part 2. Cant. 3.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>And Sage Opinions of the <hi>Moon</hi> Sells;</l>
                  <l>To whom all People far and near,</l>
                  <l>On deep importances repair;</l>
                  <l>When Braſs, or Pewter hap to ſtray,</l>
                  <l>Or Linen ſlinks out of the way;</l>
                  <l>When Cattle feel Indiſpoſition,</l>
                  <l>And need the help of a Phyſician;</l>
                  <l>When Murren reigns in <hi>Hogs</hi> or <hi>Sheep,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And Chicken languiſh of the Pip;</l>
                  <l>To him with <hi>Queſtions,</hi> and with <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They for diſcovery flock, or <hi>curing.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He had been vers'd in <hi>Aſtrology,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And was Old Dog at <hi>Phyſiology:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But though in Circle of the Arts,</l>
                  <l>He did advance his Nat'ral Parts,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:93964:9"/>
                  <l>Like Dog in Wheel, did ſtill retreat,</l>
                  <l>And fall <hi>to Juggle, Cant,</hi> and <hi>Cheat;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or as thoſe Fowl that live in Water,</l>
                  <l>Are never wet, he did but ſmatter:</l>
                  <l>Whate'er he labour'd to appear,</l>
                  <l>His <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> ſtill was clear;</l>
                  <l>Yet none a deeper Knowledge boaſted,</l>
                  <l>Since Fryar <hi>Bacon,</hi> or Old <hi>Groſted.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He with the <hi>Moon</hi> was more familiar</l>
                  <l>Than e'er was <hi>Almanack Well-willer;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her Secrets underſtood ſo clear,</l>
                  <l>That ſome believ'd he had been there;</l>
                  <l>Knew when She was in fitteſt Mood</l>
                  <l>For cutting <hi>Corns,</hi> or letting <hi>Blood;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When for anointing <hi>Scabs</hi> or <hi>Itches,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or to the Bum applying <hi>Leeches;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fright <hi>Agues</hi> into Dogs, and ſcare</l>
                  <l>With Rhymes the <hi>Tooth-ach</hi> and <hi>Catarrh;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cure <hi>Warts</hi> and <hi>Corns</hi> with application</l>
                  <l>Of Medicines to th' Imagination.</l>
                  <l>He knew the Medicine <hi>Paracelſus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Could make a Man with, as he tells us;</l>
                  <l>He knew whatever's to be known,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But much more than he knew would own.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Did not our great <hi>Reformers</hi> uſe</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Sidrophel</hi> to foreboad News?</l>
                  <l>And hath he not alway foretold</l>
                  <l>Whate'er the cloſe <hi>Committee</hi> would?</l>
                  <l>Made <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> for the Cauſe,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Moon</hi> for Fundamental Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. line 38. for <hi>He</hi> read <hi>But,</hi> p. 7. Marg. for <hi>L. H.</hi> r. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. p. 8. l. 17. r. <hi>many degrees better,</hi> p. 9. l. 19. r. <hi>diſcoverer,</hi> p. 12. Marg. r. 1652. p. 19. l. 33. for <hi>profeſſor</hi> r. <hi>poſſeſſor,</hi> p. 20. l. 2. r. 20. p. 29. l. 21.22. for <hi>Impoſtor</hi> r. <hi>Prophet,</hi> p. 41. Marg. r. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. p. 46. Marg. r. <hi>de Peſte.</hi> Some Literal Miſtakes are left to the Readers Candor.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93964:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To</hi> W— S—n.</head>
            <p>THERE is, Egregious Sir, a <hi>Quack Aſtrologer</hi> in your Houſe, who ſome Years ſince Publiſh'd a Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Reflection on me, without either Reaſon, or Provocation, ſo to do; which a Friend of mine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting to me, (for I uſed not to miſpend Time, or Money, in ſuch empty Stuff, with which his Pen hath ſurfeited the World.) I expoſtulated the Matter with him, by Letter; and demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Authority, or Reaſon for the Reproach; or an Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the Fault, or Miſtake, if it were ſuch; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of giving me any manner of Satisfaction, He, in the next Publick Effort of his fertil Pen, falls a railing, and chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, like an obnoxious Criminal; and attempted, by dint of Scolding, to Huff me out of thoſe Reſentments, which he had great reaſon to fear, would be ſevere upon him.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— Nihil eſt audacius illis</l>
               <l>Reprehenſis; iram, atque animos, à crimine ſumunt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Indeed, at <hi>firſt,</hi> I was ſo little diſpleas'd to ſee my ſelf treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a manner, ſo much to his own Shame, and <hi>Opprobrium,</hi> more than mine; that I ſlighted the <hi>Bawling Brain-ſick,</hi> till I found him at me again: And for want of new Matter, giving the People twice <hi>Sodden Cabbage:</hi> the ſame fulſom Stuff in a ſecond Almanack, which he had done in that, wherein he firſt put that Falſhood on <hi>Crato</hi> and me.</p>
            <p>The Repetition of this groundleſs Affront, (after I had charged him with the Falſhood thereof, and he had tacitly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it himſelf) made me ſteal a few Hours from other Avo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, to do my ſelf right, and ſtop the Carreer of his Scurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Pen. But ſince he denied to take notice of my Private Challenge, I could not readily think of a better way to gain that Point, that by this Publick Addreſs, and Appeal to you, <hi>who are ſo much alike and ſo near of kin to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before we engage in ſo rough and unpleaſant a way, as a cloſe and ſerious Diſcourſe of this Matter will carry us to, It
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93964:10"/>may not be amiſs to ſweeten our Humours by ſome divertive Entertainment, in the beginning of our Courſe; and becauſe ſome of his Quack Poſtures afforded me ſuch Pleaſure, that I felt little of the pinching part of his Bum-fodder; I will make you merry with a Specimen of his Worſhip's Wit, both in Verſe and Proſe.</p>
            <p>I begin with the former, not only becauſe the Pamphlet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds therewith, but for the excellency of it; being the very quinteſſence of <hi>Helicon,</hi> and Heart Blood and Guts of the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>Homer, Pindar, Virgil,</hi> or <hi>Cowley</hi> were meer Fools to <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> or <hi>Watchum,</hi> his Journeyman Poetaſter; not one of them ever made ſuch bold ſtrokes, or can ſhow ſuch Flowers, as I can, out of his doggrel and faſtidious Rhyme.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Renowned Prince! Prevail and Proſper ſtill:</l>
               <l>And make like <hi>God's Decrees</hi> your Royal Will!</l>
            </q>
            <p>There's a Bird for the <hi>King,</hi> againſt whoſe Father's Tyranny and Arbitrary Actions, he had juſt before bent his doughty Song: and now He comes to admoniſh his <hi>Majeſty</hi> to the ſame Practice. Where is the Liberty and Property of Subjects, ſo much talk'd of? If they be governed by a Prince, <hi>whoſe Will,</hi> like the Decrees of Heaven, is <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>Irreſiſtible?</hi> For ſo the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> in their Confeſſion and Catechiſms define Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination, or God's Decrees to be, <hi>viz. deſtining, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining from all Eternity, ſuch to Heaven, ſuch to Hell,</hi> (<hi>L. Du Moulin</hi> allows ſcarce <hi>One</hi> in a <hi>Million</hi> to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) <hi>without foreſight, or reſpect had, to Good, or Evil in them;</hi> but <hi>merely to ſhow his Power, and for his Glory.</hi> To imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate this, muſt be very Arbitrary, and Tyrannical! And like the Grand <hi>Louis</hi> his declared Reaſons for making his laſt War on the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and ſpilling the Blood of ſo many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, not for their Fault, but his Glory. Thus in a roaring Song againſt Arbitrary Power, which had tumbled King <hi>James</hi> out of his Throne, He recommends to King <hi>William</hi> a Walk on the ſame dangerous Precipice.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—You by your lightning Steel,</l>
               <l>Give to the ſtupid Foe a ſenſe to feel.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This is a whole Noſegay for his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> made up of as much Nonſenſe, as ever was in ſo little Meeter. He had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſcorn aſſiſtance from the <hi>Muſes</hi> in his firſt Poetical Sally in <hi>January;</hi> he hath a <hi>Furnaſſus</hi> in his own Breaſt.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93964:10"/>
            <q>
               <l>—Excludit ſanos Helicone Poetas</l>
               <l>Democritus.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>He hath a peculiar ſort of Poetry; a Specimen of which may be thus Paraphras'd in Proſe. <hi>Your Sword made the living dead,</hi> i. e. the Stupid feel, <hi>cujus Contrarium</hi>—</p>
            <q>
               <l>The Gallick fury vaniſh'd like a Ghoſt,</l>
               <l>And trembling ſtood before your Mighty Hoſt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I know not whether he intended this for Prophecy, or Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory; I am ſure it's neither Sence, nor Truth. The French have not ſhown themſelves ſuch Cowards of late, as to loſe their Courage at the ſight of an Enemy. But the Jeſt is, <hi>their fury vaniſhed, and yet ſtood trembling:</hi> There is a ſort of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in that; <hi>vaniſhing,</hi> and <hi>ſtanding; fury,</hi> and <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling,</hi> are different things. — This was in <hi>June.</hi> It ſeems the hot Weather made the <hi>Monſieurs</hi> cold, and the cool Weather heated them; for in <hi>September,</hi> he tells us they became brisk;</p>
            <q>
               <l>Threatned Revenge, and boldly ſwore.</l>
               <l>They valiant are when that no Foe is near;</l>
               <l>But always ſneak, when Enemies appear.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This was verified at the Siege of <hi>Namur;</hi> where our new <hi>Obſervator</hi> affirms, That, the Confederates, in ſeeing the Town loſt before their Faces, won more Glory,<note place="margin">1692.</note> than the <hi>ſneaking French,</hi> who took it in deſpight, and in ſight of ſuch Puiſſance as the Confederate Army, Headed by ſo great an <hi>Heroe,</hi> and <hi>Renowned Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But his choiceſt Flowers are at the end of this <hi>Gallymawfry,</hi> where he ingeniouſly mingles Poetry and Prophecy, and both of ſo true a ſtamp, as if <hi>Apollo</hi> had made him an Oracle, as well as a Poet. For my part, I don't know which to admire moſt, the Prediction, or the Rhyme.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Deceit's the Line which ſome great Men do tread,</l>
               <l>Death reigns among the Living, not the Dead.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Both theſe are for Rhyme, neither of them for Senſe, and may be thus Traveſtee'd.</p>
            <q>
               <l>There dwells no ſenſe within the Poet's head,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Death</hi> can't reign, where't hath not conquered;</l>
               <l>No more than <hi>Life</hi> can do't among the Dead.</l>
            </q>
            <p>With this ſcrap of my Muſe, we will paſs by his Poetry, and taſte a bit of his Proſe; of which he gives us a moſt delightful Morſel, in the third Paragraph of that Nonſenſe, his <hi>Geneth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liacal</hi> Conſiderations; the whole of it is a ſort of Cant and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93964:11"/>Banter, which no Man can reconcile to Sence, Reaſon, Letters, or Truth: or make Intelligible to the moſt apprehenſive Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal; much leſs the Vulgar, whom he deſign'd to captivate and amuſe by them. Pray take it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Propoſition</hi> (quoth he) <hi>is to be conſidered, and by Experience to be obſerved, whether it be true, or falſe; and if true! how near it comes to truth: or wherein, or in what parts it may vary from it.</hi> This ſenſleſs Stuff may be thus Paraphras'd. Is <hi>W. S—n</hi> in <hi>Bedlam,</hi> or not? If he be there, pray tell me how near he is to it, or how far from it? <hi>Riſum teneatis</hi>—</p>
            <p>With a whole Gorge full of the like Stuff, he crams his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in his Phyſical Advertiſement for <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Crato <hi>ſaith, That</hi> Oyl of Cloves <hi>being preſently put into a Wound, cauſeth Pain to ceaſe immediately, without Inflammation; and brings ſordid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers to a</hi> Cicatrice, <hi>and cleanſeth them; and ſtops Blood ſo admirably, that nothing doth it more, or better. If</hi> Oyl of Cloves <hi>which is ſo hot, doth this ſo abſolutely, and ſo ſafely?</hi> (Mark him, good Sir!) <hi>much more ſafely may it be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be done with</hi> Oyl of Turpentine, <hi>or any other Chymical Oyl: which is cheap, and wants ſome degrees of the heat of</hi> Oyl of Cloves. <hi>And poſſibly from this it might be that</hi> Turpentine Yonge <hi>might receive his Notion of ſtopping Bleeding with</hi> Oyl of Turpentine. Crato, <hi>it ſeems was the Author; though he is pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to attribute the whole Invention to himſelf; which a Man of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor would have abhorred to have done. Yet it is ſaid, the</hi> French, <hi>and others uſed it in the ſame caſe before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I expoſe the Falſhood of this ſenſeleſs Reflection, I muſt inform you that Seventeen Years ſince, I was prevailed on by ſuch as I could not refuſe, to Publiſh ſome Notions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Vertues of <hi>Oyl of Turpentine:</hi> Particularly, its wonderful Power to reſtrain the Bleeding of Wounds.</p>
            <p>This Diſcovery met with various Fortunes, ſome diſparaged it as a fallible and uncertain Remedy; others contemn'd it as an Old one; but many Ingenious Men honoured me with thankful Letters, together with Obſervations, confirming what I had writ concerning it; and which is Invaluable, the Famous, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> not only ſaid to Dr. <hi>R. H.</hi> and my ſelf, ſuch kind things of it, as I am too Modeſt to repeat; but He was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe pleaſed to honour it with Publick Approbation, in his Book of <hi>Specifiques.</hi>
               <note place="margin">p 160</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:93964:11"/>
            <p>I found more Envy, or Careleſneſs, than Truth, in ſuch as charged it with uncertainty, and failure; and from any of the few, who pretended they knew it before me, I could never wreſt any proof; and I do here profeſs, That in all my Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Converſation, and Travels, (which are not the leaſt) I never met it directly, or indirectly in any Circumſtance; nor had other Direction to it, than what I frankly owned, and avowed in my <hi>Preface</hi> to that Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>I am not the only Man, whoſe Labours have met ſuch diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Fate. The Great <hi>Harvey</hi>'s Diſcovery of the Circulation, was at firſt decried as a falſe Novelty by ſome; other invidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Men ſaid, the Glory of the Invention was due to <hi>Caeſalpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus;</hi> ſome, to <hi>Hippocrates;</hi> and one more Retroſpective than the reſt, eſpied it in the Writings of <hi>Solomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How unjuſtly <hi>Sidrophel</hi> hath charged me with ſtealing away the Honour due to <hi>Crato,</hi> I will now evince; and leave you to wonder, as much as I do, at the Impudence and Folly of the Reproacher.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Crato</hi> ſaith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is like thoſe Preachers, who quote St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> and never read a Father. I have peruſed all <hi>Crato</hi>'s Works, without being able to diſcover ſuch a Paſſage: nor could I reaſonably hope to find it there, knowing him to be a Man wiſer than to write ſuch Stuff. And ſurely, if <hi>Sidrophel</hi> had known where to find it, I had not been to ſeek it, and yet I muſt do him the right to confeſs, that he wanted not an Author for what he ſaid; but it's ſuch a Third-hand one; as he will be aſhamed of, if he hath any Modeſty in him? The Author I mean, is the Anonymous Tranſlator of <hi>Bonetus</hi> his Index, who ſaith, Page 660. <hi>Oyl of Cloves makes Wounds, that if it be put in preſently, their Pain imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ceaſeth without Inflammation: And it brings ſordid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers to a Cicatrice; and cleanſeth them. It ſtops Bleeding nothing more.</hi>— And for this he quotes <hi>Crato</hi> in the Margin, without naming Book, Chapter or Page.</p>
            <p>There is nothing of this originally in <hi>Bonetus;</hi> but added with many other things by the Tranſlator, taken, as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares in his Preface, out of J. G. <hi>Waltherus</hi> his <hi>Sylva Medica.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Walther Sylva Med. <hi>p. 1601.</hi>
               </note> To him I had recourſe, and in <hi>page</hi> 1601. of that laboured Work, I found theſe words, <hi>Joh. Crato l. ſing. Obſ. Med. in Ep. Ep.</hi> 97. <hi>Ol. Caryoph. praeſtat vuln. ut illorum dolor. ſi mox in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur, ſtatim ſedet &amp; abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inflamm. ad cicatr. perducat ſordida <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lc. mund. flux. &amp; vir. ſiſtet adeo ut nih. ſupr.</hi>— I have put them
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93964:12"/>down to a Letter, pointed, and abbreviated exactly as it's in the Book; that you may ſee the Inſincerity and Wickedneſs of my Antagoniſt, how little ground he had for quoting <hi>Crato,</hi> or affirming that Oyl of Cloves ſtops Bleeding, and at ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful a rate; ſo abſolutely, that nothing doth it more or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; when <hi>Crato, Waltherus,</hi> or whoever were the Author of theſe words, mean nothing of it. They ſpeak of the flux of Humours to ſordid Ulcers, not one word of the <hi>Haemorrhages</hi> from Wounds.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I am well aſſured, <hi>Crato</hi> hath no ſuch Epiſtles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant as thoſe <hi>Waltherus</hi> referrs to; becauſe in three ſeveral Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that Work, which I have examined, they are not to be found: nor is there any mention made of them by <hi>Vander Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> or in <hi>G. Merklin</hi>'s Account of the Labours of that Author, nor is there reaſon to think ſo good a Phyſician, ſo well Skilled in Natural Philoſophy, and the <hi>Materia Medica,</hi> as <hi>Crato</hi> was, could fall into ſo groſs an Error, as to think that the Chymical Oyl of an Aromatick Vegetative, hot in the third degree, as Cloves are; could cauſe ſuch ſudden, prodigious Ceſſation of Pain, in recent Wounds, and not inflame them.</p>
            <p>I know many famous Authors account it very balſamick, <hi>viz. Beguinus, Weicker, Renodeus, Gluckſtrad, Barthius, Erneſtus, Hoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Woodal,</hi> &amp;c. Some of them equal it with natural Balm, and there are three or four Writers of good Reputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, who ſpeak highly of its healing Vertue, and of its faculty to reſtrain the <hi>Haemorrhages</hi> of Wounds too, which <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drophel,</hi> had he known them, might have alledged more to his purpoſe and credit, than this Third-hand Quotation, as from <hi>Crato.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. Erneſtus</hi> much admires it,<note place="margin">De ol. Chym. p. m. 410.</note> 
               <hi>Exterius omnia recentia vulnera, punctim vel caeſim inflicta, ſanat, humiditates nervorum in iis &amp; haemorrhagias compeſcit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. J. Weickerus,</hi> writes thus of it—<hi>Omnes virtutes habet bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſami. Extrinſecus vulnera recentia ſanat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Antidot. l. 2 p. m. 655.</note> 
               <hi>vulnerum ſanguinem fluentem &amp; aquam ſiſtit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. Barthius</hi> directs a way of diſtilling an Oyl from Cloves,<note place="margin">In Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roc. <hi>Begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</hi> l. 2. c. 6.</note> to drops of which being mingled with 4 grains of <hi>Sacchar. Saturni, ulcera, &amp; vulnera mirabiliter conſolidat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>A. Libavius</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Prax. Chym. 136.</note> 
               <hi>Balſamus eſt praeſtantiſſimus, vulnera omnia fundentia, ſanguinem &amp; ſerum, quod ſupprimit.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:93964:12"/>
            <p>The truth of all which, I readily credit; declaring at the ſame time, that I derived not my Notion from <hi>Crato,</hi> or either of them; nor obtained it any other way, than what I declared in my Preface: Nor can <hi>Oyl of Cloves</hi> pretend to thoſe many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventitious Benefits, which accrew to Wounds, by the uſe of <hi>Oleum Terebinthinae;</hi> much leſs will it allay Pain in recent ones, and not heat them. To affirm that, is ſo ſenſeleſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſpenſ.</hi> l. 1. Cap. 3. Sect. 7. p. 145.</note> and void of all reaſon, that <hi>Sidrophel</hi> himſelf, methinks, ſhould not have been guilty of it, after you had told him ſo learnedly, <hi>That Cloves yield much Oyl, becauſe they have much of Sulphur and Salt in them, and that by reaſon of the Salt, the Oyl is ſharp, cauſtick, and biting.</hi> Very much ſo, ſaith <hi>M. Thybaut,</hi> from whom you ſtole the whole.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Cloves</hi> be hot in the third degree, as is by all hands allowed,<note place="margin">Theat. Bot. I. H. <hi>p 429.</hi> Hiſt. Plant. Tom. <hi>2. l. 26. cap. 2.</hi>
               </note> the Chymical Oyl muſt be more ſo; as <hi>J. Bauhinus,</hi> and our excellent Mr. <hi>Ray</hi> do alike obſerve.— <hi>E caryophyllis qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>que diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur oleum.— Eſt preculdubiò calidius multo.</hi> And conſequently muſt accend, and inflame newly divided Fleſh; unleſs we are ſuch Children to believe, that a very hot oily Sulphur will cool: and a very hot, <hi>Corroſive</hi> ſharp Salt eaſe Pain in tender Wounds. That would make us as ridiculous Naturaliſts as the old Woman, who ſaid, <hi>Pepper was hot in Operation, but cold in Working.</hi> And ſuch a one is <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> if he believe ſuch Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes; as he will find to his Pain, if ever he be ſo ſilly when he hath occaſion to experiment it on himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It brings ſordid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers to a Cicatrice, and cleanſeth them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he puts the Cart before the Horſe; for by the Rules of Surgery, <hi>ſordid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers muſt be cleanſed before they be cicatriced.</hi> But I perceive he is a Stranger to thoſe things: elſe he would neither have written ſo prepoſterouſly, nor believed (though he had had an Author for it) ſo erroneouſly as he hath done by aſſerting, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at an <hi>anodyne Medicine is detergent.</hi> We know that all Mundifiers, eſpecially ſuch as are po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent enough to cleanſe ſordid Ulcers, are ſharp, and frettin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and conſequently <hi>pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful:</hi> Such are precipitate, <hi>Mercury, V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, Verdigreaſe,</hi> &amp;c. and without doubt the Oyl now in diſpute, will appear ſenſibly ſo, when applied to Ulcers, much more to Wound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that are not ſenſeleſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It ſtops Bleeding, ſo admirably, that nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more, or better,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he tranſcends his Authors, for they do not make its Operation ſuch an admirable thing. But I know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſtretcht it,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93964:13"/>to make it tally with <hi>Oyl of Turpentine:</hi> but that won't do! though to carry on the Metaphor, he commits a moſt horrid blunder in theſe words,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Oyl of Cloves, which is ſo hot, doth this ſo abſolutely? And ſo ſafely? Much more ſafely may it be ſuppoſed to be done with</hi> Oyl of Turpentine, <hi>&amp;c. which wants ſome degrees of the heat of Oyl of Cloves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he ſeems ſenſible of the heat of Clove Oyl. It's ſtrange therefore, that <hi>Crato,</hi> or any Man, ſhould perſuade him, that its Anodyne to recent Wounds, and won't heat them. But who can be ſurpriſed at the Inconſiſtencies and Incongruities of a Man, who hath ſo little regard to Senſe, Truth, Coherence, or good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? And commits ſuch blunders in one breath, as he hath done in this ſingle Period. Oyl of Cloves ſtops Bleeding ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, that nothing doth it more, or better; it doth it <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, ſafely, &amp;c.</hi> and yet after all that ſuperlative Character, he ſuppoſeth it may be done a degree better by <hi>Oyl of Turpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine;</hi> for that will ſtop Blood more ſafely, than what doth it abſolutely, and ſafely. <hi>Oyl of Cloves</hi> is not to be exceeded, but <hi>Oyl of Turpentine</hi> is moſt excellent. If this be not <hi>Teague</hi> all over, I know not what is? What, <hi>Dear Joye!</hi> Doth <hi>Oyl of Turpentine</hi> exceed an abſolute, ſafe, incomparable Remedy? Will it ſtop Blood better than what doth it beſt of all? Can it excel that, which is not to be excelled? This is pure Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bank Rhetorick, common with <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> who hath recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the World above an hundred Remedies, every one of which is the beſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">
                  <hi>And poſſibly from this it might be, that</hi> Turpentine Yonge, <hi>might receive his Notion of</hi> ſtopping Bleeding with Oyl of Turpentine. Crato <hi>it ſeems was the Author, though he is pleaſed to attribute the whole Invention to himſelf: which a Man of Candor would have abhorred to have done.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this ſenſeleſs, and irrational Rallery, I ſhall paſs over his Nick-naming me, and his moſt Illiterate way of expreſſing himſelf, as no ſtrange thing from one over Head and Ears in the Bogs of Blunder, and Nonſence; and proceed to ſhow you the Iniquity, and ill Conſequence of his way of Inference, or concluding <hi>à Poſſe ad Eſſe,</hi> for that's his Logick; and by the ſame Rule I will undertake to prove <hi>Sidrophel</hi> to be the Son of a Whore: for it's poſſible: <hi>Ergo</hi> He is ſo. By this way of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, he accuſeth me of being Plagiary from <hi>Crato:</hi> But how
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93964:13"/>Abſurdly and Illogically is too apparent; for by it, any thing may be made good: Concluſions may be made not only repugnant to Logick, and the Rules of Perſuaſion, but to Truth it ſelf; and all things that can exiſt, are actually now in being, if his Rule be good.</p>
            <p>Beſide, the inartificial Deduction, the Inference is very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true: It was impoſſible I could ſteal that from <hi>Crato,</hi> which was never in him. If it were, why doth he not ſhow it me, when demanded? Though if he could produce it in him, it would not prove that I ſtole it thence; becauſe I never knew or heard it was there, till <hi>Waltherus,</hi> the Engliſher of <hi>Bonetus,</hi> and <hi>Sidrophel</hi> have falſly told me ſo, long ſince my Book was Publiſhed.</p>
            <p>But if I had been led by <hi>Crato</hi> to thoſe Thoughts I had of <hi>Ol. Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reb. Sidrophel</hi> confeſſeth mine exceeds his in divers particulars; and conſequently, all that advantage is owing to me; and <hi>Crato</hi> no more the Author of my Notions than the Inventor of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Glaſſes was the Author of Telleſcopes; The Pilot at <hi>Helvia,</hi> the Diſcover of <hi>America:</hi> Or he that enquired of Dr. <hi>Harvey</hi> what became of all the Blood yelpt from the left Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle of the Heart into the great Artery, was the Diſcoverer of Circulation.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Ita res accendunt lumina rebus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lucret</hi> lib. 1.</note>
            </q>
            <p>Hints may lead to Diſcoveries, but do not make them; one thing gives light to another; and the Glory of thoſe Achiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments attempted from thoſe leſſer Intimations, remain to <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lileo, Columbus,</hi> and <hi>Harvey,</hi> while the Names of thoſe firſt Luminaries, are ſunk and loſt.</p>
            <p>Furthermore! If any ſuch thing was in <hi>Crato?</hi> Why muſt I ſteal it from him, rather than <hi>Erneſtus, Wickerus,</hi> or <hi>Libavius?</hi> How comes he to be the Author of the Invention, more than they, who had ſaid it before him: And from whom, if ever he ſaid any ſuch thing, he probably took it? There is an Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Erneſtus</hi> Printed, when <hi>Crato</hi> was but 23 Years old, and <hi>R. Moreau</hi> ſaith that <hi>Wicker</hi> flouriſh'd in <hi>Baſil</hi> 1562. which was 23 Years before <hi>Crato</hi> died, about which time alſo <hi>Libavius</hi> was Profeſſor of Hiſtory, and Poetry, as <hi>Merklin</hi> tell us.</p>
            <p>But after all; It's manifeſt, that I was ſo far from arrogat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Invention, or aſſuming more than belonged to me, that in my Preface to that Book, I not only inveighed warmly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch, as Plume themſelves with others Feathers; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93964:14"/>any Claim to that particular Invention; and not only ſo, but told my Reader how the firſt Diſcoverer found it, and named the Perſon who handed it from him to me. This is ſo plain, and clear in the four firſt Pages of that Preface, that I am aſtoniſht at the Forehead of this moſt notorious and moſt infamous Plagiary! Surely no Man without <hi>Opium,</hi> could accuſe me publickly for arrogating the whole Invention, when the World knows not an Author leſs guilty of ſuch Piracy than my ſelf, or more than my Accuſer, who concludes as he began, with Falſhood and Slander.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It's ſaid the</hi> French, <hi>and others uſed it in the ſame Caſe before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he hath any Author for this Report, it's juſt ſuch another as he had for <hi>Crato:</hi> Such as he is aſhamed to own; for I am ſure, the <hi>French</hi> mention it not in any of their Writings, nor ever uſed it in their Practice, till they had it from me: Nor have any other ever pretended to it, that I know. There are many Men apt to arrogate more to themſelves than belongs to them, witneſs <hi>Sidrophel;</hi> but where's he, who will ſuffer ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to carry away his Laurels? I will therefore preſume (after ſo many Years enjoyment of the Honour which I won, by Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing, and Improving this Diſcovery) to claim it by Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, as my due; in deſpight of this invidious Gainſayer, who, fearing his fathering it on <hi>Crato</hi> would not deprive me, attempts by a ſecond Lye to give it the <hi>French.</hi> I have demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his ground for this Suggeſtion alſo, but his guilt ſtill keeps him ſilent: ſo that I conclude this alſo to be a <hi>Chimera</hi> of his own Brain, as all the reſt of his Affirmations are.</p>
            <p>Now, if there be nothing in <hi>Crato,</hi> which could beget in me, ſuch an Opinion of <hi>Ol. Tereb.</hi> as I Publiſhed; or if there were, and I ignorant of it, and conſequently not led by it; if I not only exclaimed againſt <hi>Plagiaries</hi> in general, but diſclaimed any Title to that Exploration in particular, <hi>All which are moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;</hi> What an injury hath he done me, thus to Libel and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my Name, and Reputation, without any manner of Cauſe to juſtifie it, or Foundation to ſupport it.</p>
            <p>But alas! All this is nothing compared with what the next Sally of his Pen beſtows on me. Here his Choler is only mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there his Gall overflows with ſo much rancour, and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as if one of <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> broke looſe from <hi>Bedlam,</hi> had raked <hi>Holbourn-Ditch,</hi> or the filthieſt Shore of the Town, for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93964:14"/>Dirt to caſt upon me. He reſolved, if falſe Reflections, and groundleſs Calumnies would not blacken me, to try what Smut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſcolding would do. Tranſported he was with fear of being Chaſtized for his Fault, and cunningly thought to prevent me by throwing Duſt in my Eyes, and crying Murther! like a Thief purſued by the Conſtable.</p>
            <p>This he attempts in a rude, and ſavage Epiſtle, to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Seplaſium, (Forica,</hi> or <hi>Sterquilinum</hi> had been a fitter Name for it;) but how much it blackens himſelf more than me, every Man of ſober Sence ſhall judge.</p>
            <p>I muſt own, that he honoured me with very good Company, by railing in the ſame Libel againſt the College of Phyſicians, and Men of the greateſt Reputation in Phyſick, <hi>for impoſing on the Publick, by not providing ſuch Phyſicians, and Remedies for Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Army, as he could have done; whereby great numbers in the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Expedition might have been ſaved.</hi> As much as to ſay, Why had not your Majeſty made <hi>Sidrophel</hi> Phyſician, and Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary-General to your Forces? He by his Skill, and Fidelity, would have ſaved the lives of many thouſands of your poor Subjects, who died for want of both, in the hands of ſuch ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Knaves, as the <hi>Murthering College</hi> appointed for that Service.</p>
            <p>It was my turn next, and accordingly <hi>Sect.</hi> 11. of his Preface to the ſame Libel, he falls on me; but after another manner. He doth not lay ſpilling the Blood of Men to my charge, but the Credit of <hi>Quacks,</hi> and <hi>Mountebanks.</hi> I had not been guilty of the death of thouſands (thank my Stars) as the <hi>College</hi> were: but my fault was, That I had reflected on the Ignorance of ſuch Fools, and Knaves as would be thought Phyſicians too, and ſo engroſs to themſelves only, what the Proverb divides among all Mankind; and for that he falls heavily on me after this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It may be</hi> (quoth he) <hi>ſuch an ignorant Fellow as the Naſty Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of an Impertinent Pamphlet called</hi> Medicaſter, <hi>may bedaub me, as he hath done honeſt</hi> Culpeper, <hi>who hath been at reſt theſe Forty Years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All Men are Ignorant,<note place="margin">Socrates.</note> though not all alike ſo. He was no ſmall Philoſopher, who after long Study, confeſt that <hi>he was come to know that he knew nothing.</hi> If the Book which ſo Scared, and Provoked <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> or what elſe I have written, will not convince him that I am not the moſt Ignorant Man in Nature, I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93964:15"/>hope this will: and if that fail, I dare Appeal to the moſt competent Judges in the Nation, the <hi>College of Phyſicians,</hi> and <hi>Society of Surgeons,</hi> who are the great Tribunals of our Faculty, and to whom, I have Dedicated my ſelf and This.</p>
            <p>But to call that Book a worthleſs Scribble, and its Author an <hi>Impertinent,</hi> was much out of the way: Nothing being more valuable, more proper, or more noble than to reſcue Men from Errors, and Miſtakes; and to ſcourge ſuch out of <hi>Apollo</hi>'s or <hi>Aeſculapius</hi>'s Temple, as attempt to put Falſities on Mankind, that are of ſuch danger to their lives, and the uſeful Art of Healing. This, This was the whole drift of that Book, and ſo effectually done, that I knew none it diſpleaſed; except the <hi>Quacks,</hi> who, alarmed by the deſign, I ſeemed to have, of expoſing the whole Herd of Scribbling <hi>Medicaſters,</hi> cryed out Fire! Murther! <hi>&amp;c.</hi> before they were hurt. Indeed I pointed at <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> and his Father <hi>Culpeper;</hi> at <hi>Thompſon, Harvey,</hi> and others of that Tribe; but that was all the harm I did theſe <hi>honeſt</hi> Men; and perhaps, if he had not given me this Provocation, I had ſaid no more of them. In the Liſt I hinted of that ſort of Cattle, he could pick out but three to vindicate, by which he allows my Cenſure of the reſt: And I'll prove that theſe ſelect Friends of his, are not the beſt in the Pack: Or as bad as the worſt of them, whom he left to themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Culpeper</hi> was an Impudent <hi>Quack Aſtrologer,</hi> and a Rebel. He Libelled the learned King <hi>James,</hi> and that moſt Pious Prince, and Martyr, his Son, and damn'd them both to Hell, together with the whole College who Compiled the <hi>London Diſpenſatory.</hi> Among whom were our Immortal <hi>Harvey, Gliſſon, Jordan, Mayern,</hi> &amp;c. Men of more Worth and Learning, than all the <hi>Quack Aſtrologers</hi> in <hi>Europe.</hi> Theſe famous Worthies are by <hi>Sidrophel</hi>'s <hi>Honeſt Culpeper,</hi> treated as if they were (like them) Scounderils,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> Ed. 1652. on Man. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti.</note> and pernicious Vermin. In one Page he calls them <hi>Lubbers, Blaſphemous, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nskilful, Diſhoneſt, Impudent in Sin, Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, Idolaters, Ranters,</hi> Men that Worſhip'd Old <hi>Jemmy</hi> for <hi>God,</hi> and his Son for <hi>Chriſt: But their Tutelar Gods</hi> (quoth he) <hi>being</hi> apud inferos, <hi>gives me ſome hope they will follow them quickly, and ſo all the</hi> Tyrants <hi>go together.</hi> Thus inhumanly, and in a faſhion as far from Honeſty, and Chriſtianity, as it was from Charity, or good Manners, doth this Wretch (celebrated by <hi>Sidrophel</hi>) treat the Sacred and Pious Memories of the moſt Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and beſt of Men, and moſt uncharitably and wickedly Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93964:15"/>their Souls to no leſs than Eternal Flames, a piece of Impudence never to be parallell'd but by <hi>Sidrophel</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>But you ſhall have another Evidence of <hi>Culpeper</hi>'s <hi>Honeſty,</hi> given to the World by <hi>W. Prynne,</hi> who was one of the moſt active Inſtruments to promote the Rebellion againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr, and a violent Enemy to the <hi>Proteſtant Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Fathers,</hi> not ſparing the Pious, and Learned Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher.</hi> He tells us, <hi>That thoſe two Jeſuitical Prognoſticators,</hi> Lilly,<note place="margin">True and perfect Narrative. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 60.</note> and Culpeper, <hi>were ſo confident,</hi> A. D. 1652. <hi>of the total Subverſion of the Law, and Goſpel Miniſtry, That in their Scurrilous</hi> Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtications, <hi>they Predicted the Downfal of both. And in</hi> January 1654. <hi>They Foretold that the Law ſhould be pulled down to the ground, the great</hi> Charter, <hi>and all our Liberties deſtroyed, as not ſuiting with Engliſh Men in theſe <hi>Bleſſed Times.</hi> That the Crab-Tree of the</hi> Law <hi>ſhould be pulled up by the Roots, and grow no more: There be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no reaſon we ſhould now be governed by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. D. 1652. <hi>Sidrophel</hi>'s <hi>Honeſt Culpeper</hi> Publiſhed a Libel called, <hi>Cataſtrophe Magnatum</hi> containing Treaſon enough to hang all the Empiricks, and Aſtrologers in the three Kingdoms, Railing at the Crown, Mitre, and Long Robe; inveighing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law, and Lawful Government of <hi>England;</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting the utter Subverſion of it, both in Church and State; Praiſing, and Extolling the Villanies of thoſe Execrable Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and Barbarous Regicides, who ſtand proſcribed in our Statutes, and in our Laws declared to be <hi>Sons of</hi> Belial,<note place="margin">12 <hi>Car.</hi> 2.30.</note> 
               <hi>Men hardened in Impiety; neither true Subjects, nor true Chriſtians.</hi> And ſo much for the honeſty of <hi>Sidrophel</hi>'s admired <hi>Culpeper.</hi> As to his other two Brethren whom he defends, and applauds, you ſhall have their Character too by and bye, as they come in my way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Name he thinks not worthy to live in his Work;</hi> and I thank him for it. I had rather have it in an Houſe of Office, than his <hi>Confectioners Shop.</hi> Had he uſed it any other way than he doth, he had injured me; it being better to be reviled with the <hi>College,</hi> than praiſed among ſuch infamous Fellows as <hi>Culpeper, Thomſon,</hi> &amp;c. And more Reputation to be ill ſpoken of, than commended by ſuch a Scandalous Plagiary; whoſe good word can be no Credit to any Man on whom he beſtows it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am alive</hi> (quoth angry <hi>Sidrophel</hi>) <hi>to caſtigate his Inſolence, at leaſt to trample upon his Contumelies; which I ſhall do by ſlighting his Ignorance and Malice, and not reſenting the Injury.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93964:16"/>
            <p>Here's another touch at <hi>Iriſh!</hi> And ſuch a <hi>Teague-land</hi> Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-buſs as the former.— What, Dear Joy! <hi>Caſtigate his Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and trample upon his Contumelies, without reſenting the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury? What! Slight his Contumelies,</hi> and yet all the while ſcold like any Fiſh-woman at <hi>Bilingſgate</hi> at the Author of them? Theſe things don't conſiſt; unleſs he wiſely thinks a Man may be in a Rage without Anger: Beat an Enemy without taking any notice of him: Revile, and Quarrel in pure Love: Or, to uſe his own Words, <hi>Caſtigate Inſolence, and trample on Contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, by ſlighting them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He hath no luck at all at Satyr; Therefore, good Sir, if you can't perſuade him to leave off Tranſlating,<note place="margin">This I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire may be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſuch as miſtake his Rant for good Satyr, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially <hi>a little Gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterpipe Fellow,</hi> who lives within a mile of the <hi>Gallows,</hi> and is to die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a Ropes length on't.</note> 
               <hi>(i. e. Cobling)</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Books, and Scribling Almanacks, (his two chief Talents) yet beg him to deſiſt from Satyr; for he can make none but on himſelf. He hath here attempted to be Satyrical on me, but you ſee he is like one who ſpits into the Sky; it rebounds on his own Face. They ſay <hi>a little Wit, and a great deal of ill Nature make a good Satyriſt.</hi> He hath enough of the latter; but he wants even that <hi>Modicum</hi> of the former, to compleat him. He is but an <hi>Infant Satyr,</hi> he hath Nails, but no Teeth. He can ſcratch but can't bite. In ſhort he is a <hi>Scold,</hi> not a <hi>Satyr.</hi> A <hi>Zoilus,</hi> or a <hi>Momus,</hi> not a <hi>Juvenal,</hi> or a <hi>Perſius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I, but beſides himſelf, and his dear Father <hi>Culpeper,</hi> the <hi>Silly Wretch, and Impertinent Fool that wrote <hi>Medicaſter Medicatus,</hi> hath aſſaulted the Reputation of the Learned Dr. <hi>Thomſon,</hi> and Worthy Ingenious Dr. <hi>G. Harvey:</hi> Both which had more Learning in their Little Fingers, than that Conceited Impertinent hath in his whole naſty Body, and that provoketh him to piſs upon the Puppy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pray take notice, Sir, how he ſcorns to reſent the Injury my Book did his Party. Obſerve with what Civility, Calmneſs, and Poliſht Manners, he acts the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> or the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the Affronts I put upon him and his Friends. See how Meekly he turns the other Cheek, and gives me his Cloak alſo. Poor Saint! I pity him, that he ſo ſoon diſcovers himſelf to be quite contrary to his Pretenſions, and after all his <hi>Meekneſs, Patience,</hi> and <hi>Paſſive Valour,</hi> rails, and throws about him like a <hi>Thraſher,</hi> or <hi>Kettle-Drummer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ay, but his two Darling Friends were affronted by me, and that tranſported him; nothing elſe would have moved his <hi>Ire,</hi> and ſtirred up his <hi>Wrath</hi> againſt me. I confeſs I do not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93964:16"/>at his fond Concern for his two learned Friends, becauſe I know them caſt in one Mold, <hi>They are Birds of a Feather.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomſon</hi> I ſhall ſay the leſs of, becauſe he is dead: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe while living, he was ſufficiently proved to be no <hi>Doctor,</hi> but an <hi>Illiterate Dunce;</hi> by one of the moſt Learned Phyſicians of the Age. And indeed he was obviouſly ſo to all Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Readers of his Pamphlets:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stubbs</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Thompſon.</hi> &amp;c.</note> For excepting a few hard words, the Cant and Jargon of <hi>Helmont,</hi> and an <hi>Arcanum</hi> or two, that he boaſts of, more famous for the Death, than Cure of his Patients, there is nothing at all in them: His Notions are untintelligible: His Opinions, as far as they can be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, very Erroneous: his Language Bombaſt, Affected, and very Silly: And his Aſſertions <hi>Heterodox,</hi> and <hi>Wrong.</hi> Take a few Specimens. <hi>The time is at hand</hi> (quoth he) <hi>that a Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt will be look'd upon no better than a Bronchotomiſt or Cut-throat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preface.</note> 
               <hi>Blood is the immediate Inſtrument of the Soul, in which it ſhines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s true way of preſerving the Blood, p. 2. p. 4.</note> 
               <hi>diſplaying its Radiant Beams every way; that Senſation, Motion, Nutrition, and all other Functions may be performed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Blood of Man is graduated to the higheſt Perfection, fitting to be a Receptacle of ſo Divine a Gueſt, the Immortal Soul, which as long as it is here incarcerated, lying couched in the Senſitive, being bound to act by Corporeal Organs, ſuffers many Obſcurations, Defections, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſes, through variety of Meteors ariſing in the Horizon of this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſm, from the Blood degenerate and depraved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Blood is an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Subſtance diviſible only by ſome external,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 6.</note> 
               <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental means, as the Air or Fire, which cauſes a various Texture and different Poſition of its Atoms,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>Both of theſe do ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly larvate and diſguiſe this puniteous Balſom,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Did they rightly underſtand how Blood like Mercury might be Polymor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 6.</note> &amp;c. <hi>theſe Dogmatiſts would never be ſo forward to pierce poor Mans Skin, raſhly let out, and throw away the ſubſtantial ſupport of Life,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The efficient Cauſe or Agent of Blood is the innate Archeus or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 9.</note> 
               <hi>which chiefly makes this formal tranſmutation of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is nouriſhable. This works by his principal Inſtrument, the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Duumvirate, and in the reſt of the Digeſtions. For this</hi> Primum Mobile, <hi>moving</hi> ſine Motore alieno, <hi>ſets all the other Wheels in Motion, till being exantlated, and its Vital Power exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, all the inferiour Orbs forthwith ſubſiſt, are at a ſtand and fail. This</hi> Autokineton <hi>is the Seat or Subject of the Senſitive Soul, where it is emicant and tranſlucent in the ſame manner as the Beams of the Sun received in by the Air in a ſerene, clear Sky, are effulgent and bright;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93964:17"/>but in a cloudy dusky Heaven are offuſcated and opacous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If timely prevention be not made, either by potent ſtrength of Body,<note place="margin">p. 12.</note> or a prevalent Art, the Man decays in his Faculties, the Archeus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes aculeated, extimulated, and becomes exorbitant, framing va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Exotick, Morbifick Idaeas, cauſing a Syndrom of Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clite Symptoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The next notable Cauſe that makes great alteration for the worſe in this Vital Juice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 14.</note> 
               <hi>are the extravagant Perturbations, Storms and Tempeſts that ariſe in this</hi> Microcoſin, <hi>raiſed through miſapprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, miſapplications, and miſinterpretations of things obvious to our Senſe, contrived by a <hi>luxated</hi> or <hi>diſlocated</hi> imagination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This feral Brat of Hell, Melancholy, doth diſturb the Oeconomy of the Soul's reſidence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 15.</note> 
               <hi>and is the Original of a black fuliginous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anger intoxicates, pourtraying the perfect Idea of Madneſs, which ſometimes is ſo graduated, that no Poyſon in this part of the World ſeems to be more active, for a few Atoms of this venomous Gore penetrating the cutaneous Membrane, hath infected the whole ruddy Maſs, introducing moſt truculent Symptoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If we be not Maſter of our unruly Paſſions, it is impoſſible there ſhould be an Eutomie, an Eucraſie, and Eumetry in this Solar Juice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diſeaſes are firſt embryonated and characterized in the Vital Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p.27.</note> 
               <hi>reſiding in the Hypocondries, Stomach, and Spleen,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An inveterate pain of the Head takes its firſt beginning from the enormon of the Duumvirate, where the ſeminal Rudiments and Idea of this Diſeaſe were abumbrated or ſhadowed forth by the ſenſitive Soul, excited to Paſſion upon the apprehenſion of ſomething diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and injurious to Vitality. Afterward the ſame is perfectly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineated in the Archeus of the Brain in which the Scene laid below is now brought to light above. Now is to be ſeen a Syndrom of many Symptoms, which plainly ſhew the Nature of the Diſeaſe ſuitable to the part afflicted. Here the Latex and Vital Juice apoſtalize by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees from their purity, the Ferments,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As the Soul inhabits the Archeus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 28.</note> 
               <hi>ſo this is permanent in the Blood, and all three take up for their</hi> Metropolitan <hi>or chief place of Reſidence, the Stomach and Spleen, in which the Soul by means of the Duumvirate, acts freely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Epiſpaſtick of</hi> Cantharides <hi>being laid on,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 39.</note> 
               <hi>where there is Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, the Skin in a ſhort ſpace is ſeparated from the Fleſh by an acrimonious Ichor, which the Archeus fabricated, being put into a fretting condition upon the apprehenſion of this virulent I laiſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:93964:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Nothing is more congenerous, ſymbolizing with the Animal Gas of Life, than highly exalted Spirit of Wine, being forthwith im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 44.</note> 
               <hi>united, and identified one with another, by reaſon of their Affinity and Congruity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phyſicians do not truly underſtand the energy of</hi> Zymoſis, <hi>what a powerful alterity is made by it, and how the ſulphureous Particles of the Vegetables becomes <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinous like the Spirit of the Animal, whereby it is enabled to profligate the Morbifick Matter through all the Emunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, Sluces, and ſecret Paſſages of the Body; This is the direct way of curing Fevers fundamentally, though they conclude the Fate of ſuch muſt needs be ſad, when ſuch Preſumptuous</hi> Phaeton-<hi>like Pyrotechniſts, drive the Mettleſom Horſes of the Sun of this</hi> Microcoſm <hi>ſo furiouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet with all this Ignorance, he had ſuch a ſtock of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, as to encounter that Prodigy of Learning above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named: <hi>But his Heart was too big for his Head.</hi> It was ſuch an <hi>Impar congreſſus,</hi> that I pitied to ſee the poor forward Creature ſo overmatcht, and baffled; ſo publickly expoſed, and charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Ignorance in the Writings of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> or <hi>Galen,</hi> and all the very Rudiments of Phyſick, without one word to ſay in his own behalf, which did not confirm the Imputation his Antagoniſt publickly laid on him.</p>
            <p>As to his ſurviving Friend <hi>G. H. — y,</hi> He, like himſelf, hath been many Years a buſie Scribbler of Heterodox Opinions and Principles in Philoſophy and Phyſick; proſtituting the Noble Art of Healing, and Libelling the moſt Famous Practicers, and Eminent Profeſſors of it, in this Age and Nation; <hi>viz.</hi> Such as Sir <hi>Th. Brown,</hi> Dr. <hi>Charlton, Cox, Willis, Lower, Short;</hi> not ſparing the moſt Learned <hi>College of Phyſicians, London.</hi> Men, whoſe Books he was not worthy to carry after them: If you would ſee the Philoſophy and Learning that was in the Head of him (I meddle not with that in his little Finger, becauſe <hi>Sidro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel</hi> writtily ſaith, there is too much for me) read his <hi>Archiolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia Philoſophica nova:</hi> If his Manners, Civility, and good Breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you need not go ſo far, as he did for it, it's abundantly expreſſed in his <hi>Caſus Med. Chir.</hi> and his <hi>Conclaves:</hi> If his Skill, you may have a lumping Penniworth in the reſt of his Faſtidious Scribbles; and if in all of them put together, you do not ſee the true ſhapes of a Scholar, a Gentleman, and a Phyſician drawn by his own hand, (Painters ſeldom hit their own Faces, nor Aſtrologers their Fates) behold him done to the Life by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Dialogue between <hi>Philiater</hi> and <hi>Momus,</hi> printed in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1687.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93964:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>De mortuis nil niſi bonum,</hi> is a Rule, quoth he, <hi>our little Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſligate</hi> is unacquainted with: And why? Becauſe I ſaid <hi>Culpeper</hi> was one of the Scribbling <hi>Medicaſters</hi> of the Age. Was he not ſo? Did he deſerve to be well ſpoken of when dead, who had done ſo much miſchief when alive; and was ſo uncharitable to the Souls of his deceaſed <hi>Sovereigns,</hi> as to place them in Hell? Beſides reproaching Their Names, and blackening Their Reputations without Truth, or Humanity, after they were laid in their Sepulchers? It ſeems, he was not acquainted with this Rule, nor <hi>Sidrophel</hi> with the other part of it, <hi>Nil niſi ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum de vivis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have been told that a Scholar once complaining to the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, that his Drink was dead, had the ſame <hi>Reprimand</hi> from the cunning Ale-tap, which I had from <hi>Sidrophel: Nil niſi bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num de mortuis.</hi> Now either the Wag was in the right, or I not in the wrong: Take your choice.</p>
            <p>But to be more cloſe and ſerious with him in this matter, I muſt tell him, his Rule is not general; it's in many caſes a fault to follow it, and our Duty to ſay evil of ſuch dead, as were notorious for committing it when alive. For this we have many Examples in <hi>Scripture,</hi> the Writings of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> the <hi>Anathema's</hi> and <hi>Cenſures</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> againſt <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>Heterodox</hi> Men. In our <hi>Statutes,</hi> inſtances of it often occur againſt Traytors, Rebels, and pernicious Men, ſuch as <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, Bradſhaw,</hi> and <hi>Ireton,</hi> who ſtand branded with very evil Characters, after they had been long dead, and their Heads on <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> as you may ſee 12. <hi>Car.</hi> 2.30.</p>
            <p>Had he minded <hi>Ludlow,</hi> and other late Libellers of King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Martyr,</hi> of this Adage, it had been pertinent. For they, contrary to all the Rules of Chriſtianity, Humanity, good Manners, and Truth it ſelf, have reproacht the Reputation of that moſt Pious Proteſtant Prince, who ſtands celebrated in many of our Statute Laws, and is Yearly by our <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and biggeſt part of the Nation, recognized, and ſolemnly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be <hi>a Righteous, Pious, Innocent Prince, and Martyr;</hi> whom yet their venomous Pens call, <hi>Tyrant, Pharaoh, Nimrod, Nero,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But I cannot forbear wondering with what Face <hi>Sidrophel</hi> could affirm, in the midſt of all this horrid <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> and ſuch a ſtorm of Fury and Scolding, That <hi>it was unchriſtian, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manlike, to ſling Dirt upon any one.</hi> Doth he not by an <hi>ore tenus</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:93964:18"/>confeſs himſelf inhumane, and unchriſtian? Or doth he think that to call a Man in the Face of the whole World, <hi>Ignorant, Malicious, Naſty, Impertinent, Scurrilous, Inſolent, Senſeleſs, Fool, Dog, Wretch, Whiffling Cur, Snarling Puppy, Profligate, Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent,</hi> &amp;c. and to crowd all this stuff into one Page of an <hi>Octavo</hi> Book, was not flinging Dirt on a Man, but giving him Sugar Plumbs? One of them muſt be his Belief, and I don't much care which it is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To caſt Dirt upon the Dead, is an Incivility not to be forgiven,</hi> quoth he; and he is the firſt that ever made expoſing <hi>Quacks</hi> to be the ſin againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> If what he ſaith be true, every Grave-maker is daily guilty of it in a literal, and every Controvertiſt, and Oppoſer of Hereſie, in a Moral Sence. And nothing is more common in the scribbles of thoſe <hi>Chymiaſters,</hi> and Star Doctors themſelves, than to rail at all the Phyſicians, except a few Maggoty <hi>Helmontians,</hi> and <hi>Aſtrological Quacks,</hi> that have been in the World theſe Sixteen hundred Years; as <hi>Men who have acted by miſchievous Rules, and killed their Patients by ill Methods, and Medicaments.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 3.</note> His Freind <hi>Thomſon</hi> in particular ſpeaks it in plain <hi>Engliſh.</hi> And his Father <hi>Culpeper</hi> in <hi>Latin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But did I abuſe the dead by placing <hi>Culpeper</hi> (<hi>Thompſon</hi> was then alive) among the empty Scribblers in Phyſick? No, all the Learned Phyſicians in <hi>England</hi> are of my Mind, and can think no otherwiſe of ſo Ignorant, ſo Rude, ſo Pragmatical a <hi>Traytor,</hi> as he was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sidrophel</hi> concludes this huffing Paragraph, with pronouncing me <hi>Senſeleſs,</hi> and <hi>Nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt, I do not, as he and ſome other vaunting <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piricks</hi> do, pretend to more Sence than comes to my dividend; nor will I own him ſo much in the right, as to think that I am wholly deſtitute of any at all: That Scandal is notorious to all that know me, or have ſeen what I have written: And even by this <hi>Reproof,</hi> it will appear, that I am Profeſſor of Sence enough, to ſhow that he hath leſs than he pretends to: and that all he hath, amounts to little more than none at all. And as to the Subject of our Conteſt, I have referred the Matter to a Tribunal, at whoſe Bar he dares not Appear, nor Appeal.</p>
            <p>Nor am I ſo little, as to juſtifie his accounting me <hi>Nothing.</hi> I have the Honour to be in the Friendſhip, Eſteem, and Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence of the moſt Eminent of the <hi>College,</hi> and <hi>Surgeons Hall;</hi> and had a Freedom in the Latter conferred on me <hi>Gratis,</hi> without
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93964:19"/>Examination, or any way of Purchaſe. I have been Phyſician, and Surgeon to a publick Hoſpital near 21 Years; and much longer ſerved my <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> in all the Military Offices my Profeſſion could Capacitate me. I have ſerved in the <hi>Navy,</hi> in the <hi>Army,</hi> in a great <hi>Garriſon,</hi> and <hi>Dock-Yard.</hi> And beſides all this, I preſide in the Civil Government of one of the biggeſt Corporations in <hi>England.</hi> And if notwithſtanding all this, I am <hi>Nothing, Sidrophel</hi> is much leſs than nothing: That is, an <hi>Almanack maker,</hi> and one who Scribbles for Bread, or to a worſe purpoſe.</p>
            <p>What that is, will appear in the Remarks I am next to make: Which will as fully detect his Knavery to the Publick, as the former doth his Folly to me. He out-doth the Proverb, and is both <hi>Fool, Knave,</hi> and <hi>Phyſician</hi> too. And that you may be ſure to ſee him all over, and know him in which of thoſe ſhapes ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he appears, I will take off his <hi>Fools Coat,</hi> and put on him that of <hi>W. Lilly;</hi> which fits him ſo exactly, that it's hard to know the one from the other. Their Reſemblance in Art, and the uſe they make of it, is the ſame: Their Contempt, and Affront of King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Martyr,</hi> is alike: One affirms him <hi>juſtly Executed;</hi> the other thought the <hi>Anniverſary</hi> enjoyned by Law for that <hi>Excerable Murder,</hi> not worth a place in his Calendar; nor his Name fit to ſtand in the noble Liſt of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne</hi> 7.</note> while yet he obtrudes ill Company on that <hi>Glorious Army,</hi> and thruſts among them ſuch odious, and deſpicable Celebrations, as that of a <hi>Quack's Nativity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But their greateſt ſimilitude lyeth in a <hi>Hieroglyphical Prophecy</hi> againſt the Throne and Church of <hi>England,</hi> publiſhed many Years ſince by the one, and now inculcated to the World by the other. It's true that ſince he heard how his contempt of the <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> in his former Almanacks, and thoſe Prophetick Emblems, were two faulty things I took notice of, He hath laboured to put a ſham Interpretation upon the one, and amend the other, by noting on the 30th of <hi>January</hi> K. <hi>Ch.</hi> I. <hi>Dec.</hi> that is, beheaded, or Executed, as <hi>Lilly,</hi> and the reſt of that Tribe uſed to word it, which is next to ſaying nothing, or worſe.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Democratical Hieroglyphick</hi> pretends to contain the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State of <hi>England</hi> for an Hundred Years, beginning 1650. half of which being paſt, and gone, his <hi>future Tenſe</hi> is become <hi>Preterimperfect;</hi> and he <hi>fatum poſt fata canebat,</hi> foretels things already come to paſs, which every Fool can do. But Folly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93964:19"/>apart! Let us examine the Knavery of this Emblematical Withcraft; and I think the expired part, will make a Key to that which is yet unfulfilled. Mark then!</p>
            <p>It begins with an <hi>Executioner,</hi> and his Sword bloody; others cutting down <hi>Royal Oak Trees,</hi> and a Crown over (not on) a Man's Head, another lying dead, as in State; and upon him a <hi>Scepter, Sword,</hi> and <hi>three Crowns;</hi> then comes a Crowned Drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon with a Scepter in his right Claw— It's eaſie to unriddle the meaning of all this, being in plain <hi>Hieroglyphical Engliſh,</hi> the Murther of King <hi>Charles,</hi> and <hi>Cromwell</hi> the Dragon aſſuming the Government— What follows reſembles the Tranſactions, and Accidents of thoſe Times. But the Sting is in the Tail, and doth not yet appear; although a Man with half an Eye may ſee the meaning of it, Mauger the Varniſh he would gloſs it, and delude us withal.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> or part to come of this Tragical Buſineſs, is a <hi>Magnificent</hi> Palace, <hi>before whoſe Gates lie ſeveral dead Dogs, Wolves, and other Beaſts of Prey, with their Heads ſeparated from their Bodies.</hi> Theſe I take to be <hi>Courtiers</hi> turn'd out of <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and Murthered at its Gate, as King <hi>Charles</hi> was. Then appears an <hi>Aſſembly of Men ſitting in an Houſe like a State-Houſe; three of them in long Robes; over the Head of one written</hi> PAX; <hi>of another</hi> LEX; <hi>and of the third</hi> GREX; not a word of REX. Then appear <hi>Men undermining the Foundations of many Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi> Churches; <hi>ſome of which fall, others are falling:</hi> Then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears <hi>a Man pulling a Surplice over a</hi> Biſhop's <hi>Ears.</hi> There's <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> gone at a daſh. Then you ſee <hi>a great Imperial Crown broken into pieces, and with it many other little Crowns and Coronets;</hi> there's <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>Nobility</hi> mumbled. Then the Swords are beaten into Plow-Shears, and the Spears into Pruning-Hooks, and all ends with Victory, and Triumph over <hi>Monarchy, Epiſcopacy,</hi> and <hi>Nobility:</hi> And then <hi>Hey Boys up go we!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For to what purpoſe elſe can it be, that this is ſo Yearly publiſhed, and repeated, but to Influence Peoples Minds in this Nation (ſo long famous for being deluded by Prophecies) with an Opinion that the <hi>Crown, Mitre,</hi> and <hi>Coronet,</hi> are by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven deſtin'd to Deſtruction; and conſequently muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to, if not promoted? That the People of this Nation have been often drawn into Rebellion by ſuch bantering De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, and Dreams of Aſtrologers, is abundantly reported by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93964:20"/>our Hiſtorians; out of whom anon you ſhall have numerous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. It was to theſe Deluders, that <hi>Wales</hi> owed that La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable Ruin it ſuffered in the days of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. and to them we are not a little indebted for the Miſeries this Kingdom hath ſuffered within few Years before the Date, or Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Prophetick Emblem, by which <hi>Sidrophel</hi> ſeems to be carrying on the <hi>Tragedy</hi> his Predeceſſors began. <hi>The fall of Churches,</hi> the <hi>diveſting of Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>breaking in pieces the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Crown of</hi> England (for there's the <hi>Scene</hi>), too plainly tell us what he would be at. And to make the unfulfilled part the more credible, he cunningly orders it ſo, that the firſt is already verified, and come to paſs. This Device, or Banter he borrowed from, or wrote in imitation of that <hi>Arch-Impoſtor</hi> and falſe <hi>Fortune-teller, W. Lilly,</hi> who at the end of a Peſtilent Pamphlet, which he calls, <hi>Monarchy or no Monarchy</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> written 1651. gives ſuch Prognoſticating Pictures as thoſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>Sidrophel.</hi> There's <hi>the Mob Aſſaſſinating Gown-Men, ſome</hi> Biſhops, <hi>and Epiſcopal Clergy tumbling down Pulpits and all. Others of them lying proſtrate on the ground; there are three Crowus and a Coronet turn'd upſide down; there are his Twins and Dragons, flaming Towns, Fleets, Graves, dead Corps, lean Cattle, Streams of Blood, a</hi> red <hi>Sea of</hi> green <hi>Blood,</hi> and all the Scare-crow, Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear Emblems of future Vengeance on the Church, Throne, and Nobility; which he had Predicted in that lying Book, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the thing had come to paſs.</p>
            <p>I call it a <hi>lying Book,</hi> on many accounts: One of which is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry notorious, and remarkable, for though it were written to Predict the final Extirpation of Monarchy, from the Murther of King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Martyr;</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 62.</note> there is a Prophecy in it, that within Fifty Years of that time, a King <hi>Henry</hi> of this Nation, ſhould Conquer <hi>France,</hi> and that he ſhould be twice Crowned. This <hi>Merlinus Liberatus</hi> takes notice of in his Almanack 1692. as a Prophecy to be perform'd by K. <hi>William.</hi> Be that true, I am ſure the Prophet was falſe. For how could there be no more Kings in <hi>England?</hi> and yet a King of this Nation, within Fifty Years after the fatal Period of Monarchy among us, atchieve ſo mighty a thing? But his Pen was like his Name, nothing but <hi>Lyes;</hi> and ſo is <hi>Sidrophel</hi>'s too. Their <hi>Hieroglyphicks</hi> are alike, their Deſigns ſeem to have the like Tendency, Date, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement, and <hi>Cataſtrophe.</hi> And the Authors alike, a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Canting Deluders, and falſe Prophets; who I hope and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93964:20"/>pray may be alike miſtaken, and confounded, and our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Church, and State, abide for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although an Aſtrologer, or an Almanack-maker be a thing odious enough to the wiſe part of the Nation, by the Falſities and Deluſions they yearly put upon them; yet foraſmuch as all Men are not enough ſenſible thereof, and many that are ſo, do yet encourage the Cheat to wicked purpoſes, I will undertake to undeceive the one, and expoſe the other, by a brief Cenſure of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> and ſetting it in ſuch a Light, as any Man with half an Eye may ſee through it, and diſcern the Vanity, and Falſeneſs thereof, and the Wickedneſs of thoſe who Practiſe, and Profeſs it; particularly <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> whom I will here expoſe as an Aſtrologer, and hereafter as a Quack, in a ſecond part of <hi>Medicaſter Medicatus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In doing which, I ſhall not meddle with all the trifling, and ſottiſh Fancies, which the Brains of <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> (fertil in Fiction) have conceived of the Stars, and thoſe Spacious Nothings, the 12 Houſes, or Caſtles in the Air; being things, which ought rather to be laught at, as the Whimſies of Men, who have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven their Imaginations liberty to commit the greateſt Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies in <hi>Bedlam;</hi> or the Crotchets of ſuch Crafty Pates, as laugh at all thoſe who do not laugh at them: But offer againſt it theſe weighty unanſwerable Objections.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>If Aſtrology were true, there is yet no true Aſtrologer, becauſe they have no certain</hi> Foundation <hi>at all:</hi> The <hi>Ephemerides,</hi> and Aſtronomical Tables by which they Calculate, being by their own Confeſſion falſe, and conſequently there Schemes no better than <hi>Poor Robins. Morinus, Agrippa, P. Cavino, Gaſſendus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aſtrol. Gal.</note> 
               <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubin, Hevelius, Ricciolus,</hi> and many other learned Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers do affirm this. And beſides, the better ſort of Aſtrologers themſelves, ſuch as <hi>Morinus</hi> the French-Man, who pretends to have made all new Rules of Aſtrology, becauſe the former were all of them falſe, and fooliſh; the moſt Illiterate of thoſe Impoſtors ſay the ſame thing. <hi>Partridge</hi> chargeth all the Tables before his own, with falſhood; and you, ſweet Sir, ſenſible that all extant are uncertain, and erroneous, promiſe to publiſh New and Correct ones.<note place="margin">Rob. God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>writes</hi> Altrologia Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta <hi>A.D.</hi> 1696.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In the Nature, Property, and Influence of the Stars, Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Zodiack, Twelve Houſes, and firſt Elements of their Art, they do not agree.</hi> So that all their Judgments are as falſe, and uncertain, as their Calculations; much more ſo, if there be no
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93964:21"/>
               <hi>Zodiack</hi> in the Heaven, nor an Heaven for ſuch a <hi>Zodiack;</hi> but that all their noiſe of <hi>Trigons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Merc. Vol. 1. n. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Triplicities,</hi> &amp;c. be as the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> call them, <hi>a fardle of Gibberiſh Nullities, invented on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to abuſe the credulity of Children, and Fools.</hi> Their dividing the Heaven into 12 parts,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>More</hi>'s Myſt. of Iniquity p. 349.355. alſo his Anſw. to <hi>Butler,</hi> 105. <hi>Gaſſend.</hi> c. 8. p. 722. Vol. 1.</note> is without Reaſon, or Mathematicks: Their qualification of the Stars, without Philoſophy: and both mere imagination, as vain as Vanity it ſelf, ſaith the greateſt Mathematician of this Age.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The new, and approved Syſtem of</hi> Copernicus, <hi>the Myriads of Stars unknown to former Ages,</hi> quite confound all the old Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Their Mutual Railing at one anothers Ignorance, Error, and Knavery;</hi> even to the heighth of <hi>Billingſgate,</hi> like <hi>Gadbury</hi> and <hi>Partridge,</hi> yearly, if we muſt believe them all, proves them all ſuch. <hi>Augur ridet Augurem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> tells us, <hi>That their Art contains no one Fundamental,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Op. Refor. <hi>Praef.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>which is not oppugned by ſome one or more of its Profeſſors.</hi> And <hi>Partridge</hi> himſelf ſpeaks out pat to the point, <hi>He that would laugh at Aſtrology</hi> (quoth he) <hi>need not read</hi> Heminga, <hi>&amp;c. but our own Authors; our Rules are ſo deficient, that they are not to be relied on, they thwart one another; our</hi> Aphoriſms <hi>are falſe, and involve us into a</hi> Labyrinth, <hi>which makes us</hi> Ridiculous.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Their different Opinions, in Prognoſticating and Predicting counter to one another, according to the Times, or the Intereſt they are of, ſhews their Ignorance, or Knavery, and the Vanity of their Art.</hi> The Inſtances of their contradictory Preſagings, are very numerous. The moſt famous of late are to be found in <hi>Wharton,</hi> and <hi>Lilly, Gadbury,</hi> and <hi>Partridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Nor are they more divided among themſelves than they are from Truth.</hi> The falſeneſs of their Prognoſtications in former Ages, are remarkt by <hi>Cicero, Pliny,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and others: Thoſe ſince, by the noble <hi>Picus, Heminga, Angelis, Gaſſendus,</hi> and many more. For it's not only thoſe little mean Fellows, who now-a-days make Almanacks, that prove the truth of this Reflection every Year: But ſuch Maſters as <hi>Albumazer, Cardan, Gaurichius, Noſtradamus,</hi> and <hi>Lilly;</hi> they have convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the World, that the Art is not able to help them to the Knowledge of any Accident before hand. They ha'n't ſo much foreſight of Weather as a Shepherd, or a Sinner that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth an Almanack in his Bones; or an old Woman with Corns on her Toes. Perhaps they'll tell you (as they do every Year)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93964:21"/>at ſuch a time as this; That <hi>great Preparations for War, and Conſultations will be made next Winter; That Fleets, and Armies will be abroad next Summer, and ſome Battel fought, or a Town taken or beſieged: That about next</hi> December, (as <hi>Merlinus Liberatus</hi> lately foretold) <hi>There will be buſineſs at the</hi> Old Baily, <hi>and that ſeveral aged People will die, in and about</hi> London. At ſuch a ridiculons rate, who may not turn Prognoſticator?</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Fatidicus non eſt qui manifeſta canit.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>I have read all <hi>Lilly</hi>'s Almanacks from 40 to 60, in the Holy time of that great <hi>Rebellion,</hi> to which he was acceſſary; and find him always the whole breadth of Heaven wide from Truth. Scarce one of his Predictions verified, but a Thouſand contrariwiſe. It's hard that a Man ſhooting at Rovers ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Years together, ſhould never hit the right Mark. In one of his Almanacks Dedicated to the <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> a very few Months before the Army (thoſe Legions of their own raiſing) tore them in pieces to the very <hi>Rump,</hi> He told them <hi>their Duration would be long, in Settlement and Peace, and that they ſhould do much good to the Kingdom, and accord with the King;</hi> Who was then cloſely confined by the Votes of <hi>Non-Addreſſes</hi> to <hi>Carisbrook-Caſtle.</hi> And but four Months before the Execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Murther of that Pious Prince, He wrote, That <hi>the King ſhould be reſtored to his former Dignity:</hi> That <hi>the Parliament,</hi> full of Honourable, and Loyal Intentions, <hi>would end all things in a general Agreement, and Reconciliation.</hi> But no ſooner was that <hi>Black Tragedy</hi> acted, and the Sword aſſumed the Crown, but he chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Tune. Then we were to have no more <hi>Kings</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and</hi> Charles <hi>the Second ſhould die before he was</hi> 38 <hi>Years old: That the</hi> Ottoman <hi>ſhould ruin the</hi> Emperor, <hi>and</hi> Venetians, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Year</hi> 70. With abundance more of ſuch Lying Stuff were his Almanacks filled, till the <hi>Reſtauration,</hi> of which he foretold not one ſyllable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Gadbury,</hi> deceived by <hi>Lilly,</hi> or ſome ſuch lying Spirit as led him, foretold alſo in an Almanack near 75. that about 80. <hi>the Turks would make a mighty inrode to</hi> Germany; <hi>That</hi> Vienna <hi>ſhould be taken by them, and they puſh their Victory home to the</hi> Belgick <hi>Shore.</hi> When contrariwiſe, about that time, the <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>Venetians</hi> made ſuch Monſtrous, and incredible Impreſſions on the <hi>Turks,</hi> as recovered all the <hi>Morea, Hungary,</hi> and a great part of <hi>Greece.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:93964:22"/>
            <p>In former Ages, when <hi>Aſtrology</hi> was more uſed, and better underſtood, they were guilty of the ſame Miſtakes, and Falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. <hi>Caeſar, Pompey,</hi> and <hi>Craſſus,</hi> whoſe Fates were Violent, Immature, and Tragical, were promiſed by thoſe Diviners, that they ſhould die aged, at their own Houſes, in Peace and Honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. Picus Mirandula</hi> ſaith he examined many of their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, and found ſcarce one in twenty prove true.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Praefac.</hi> Molin.</note> 
               <hi>Joſeph Scaliger</hi> tells us that <hi>Albumazer</hi> predicted that Chriſtianity would laſt but 1460 Years. <hi>Ab. Judaeus</hi> foretold the coming of the Meſſias ſhould be <hi>A. D.</hi> 1464. <hi>Arnoldus,</hi> That Antichriſt would appear 1345. and that <hi>A. D.</hi> 1174. the <hi>Arabian, Jewiſh,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Aſtrologers</hi> all agreed, that the utmoſt Deſolation of the World by Tempeſt, would happen <hi>A. D.</hi> 1186. How falſe theſe Predictions were, time hath ſhewn the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sextus ab Heminga</hi> collected thirty Eminent Nativities, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated by the beſt Rules of this lying Art, and they proved all falſe by Experience, <hi>ſad Events happening to thoſe on whom the Heavens</hi> by the Rules of Aſtrology <hi>ſmiled;</hi> and happineſs to ſuch as they <hi>frowned</hi> upon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cardan</hi> and <hi>Gaurichius</hi> both Calculated the Nativity of <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. who was ſlain in his fortieth Year,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cauſin</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Court, p. 360.</note> by a Splinter of <hi>Mongome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s Launce; though one of them ſaid, He ſhould live to an happy old age: and the other, that if he ſurvived the great <hi>Climaterick</hi> Year, he ſhould live gloriouſly to 70.</p>
            <p>Both did the like with <hi>Luther,</hi> and were both alike miſtaken.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cardan,</hi> who (as <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> ſaith) was a Man of the beſt Wit, Brains, and Learning of any Aſtrologer, ſpent an hundred hours on the Birth of our <hi>Edward</hi> 6th; and after all that Induſtry, was ſcandalouſly miſtaken in his Fate;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gaſſend.</hi> p 748. lib. 1 <hi>de quad.</hi> c. 2. Sect. 13.</note> for He died in his 16th Year, who by the Aſtrologer's Calculation, ſhould not be ſick till his 25th, and after that die of a <hi>Flux,</hi> and a <hi>Fever. Si vis divinare, contrarium ei ad unguem dicito, quod Aſtrologi aut polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centur, aut minitantur,</hi> was the ſaying of <hi>Martianus,</hi> not only commended, but verified by <hi>Cardan:</hi> Who after all his Skill, confeſt that ſcarce one of their Predictions in forty proved true:<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>de Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic.</hi> cap. 6. <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> More <hi>Myſt.</hi> p. 356.</note> So that the beſt of them can't forbear owning themſelves no Wizards; they all ſeem <hi>Infatuated,</hi> and more under the Power of Witchcraft than above it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. R. Camerarius,</hi> was as much out in his Judgment upon the Nativity of <hi>Henry</hi> 4th; and <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> relates how much <hi>Noſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:93964:22"/>was miſtaken in his <hi>Genethliacs</hi> on the Scheme of <hi>Suffre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> his Nativity. For to him all things happened quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Lying Predictions of that famous <hi>Aſtrologer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if ſuch <hi>Maſters</hi> in the Art, had not Skill enough to avoid ſuch groſs Miſtakes, What can be expected from ſuch half witted Aſtrologers as <hi>Merlinus Liberatus,</hi> and <hi>Sidrophel</hi> who every Year expoſe themſelves to this Cenſure? And as for Friend <hi>John,</hi> the humble Servant of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> all the many Calculations in his <hi>Collect. Genet.</hi> are accuſed of Falſhood by his Brother <hi>Partridge. Opus Reformatum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Their not foreſeeing the moſt remarkable Events, ſufficiently ſhows the Vanity of their Art, and their own Ignorance.</hi> This is manifeſt in the great Accidents of the laſt Thirty Years; <hi>the Reſlauration of King</hi> Charles II. <hi>the Plague and Fire of</hi> London; <hi>the treble War</hi> 1666. Oates<hi>'s Plot; the great Snow</hi> 1681. and the Froſt 1683. the Death of King <hi>Charles,</hi> and the Fate of his <hi>Brother;</hi> the Stupendous <hi>Revolution</hi> 1688. the Death of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. the Dukes of <hi>Newburgh,</hi> and <hi>Lorrain,</hi> who were the grand Pillars of the Confederacy, and died in one Year; the great, and Marvellous turn of Affairs in <hi>Auſtria, Hungaria,</hi> and the <hi>Morea;</hi> the many terrible Earthquakes in <hi>Jamaica, Sicilia, Naples, Flanders,</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> and the Death of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> were things our <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> foreknew no more, than <hi>Lilly</hi> could Divine who ſhit at his Door. Think you that <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> ſo cunning a Conjurer as he would be thought, if he had foreſeen the time of that great Ladies Death, would have placed <hi>Lawrels</hi> on her Brow, and told her of their being always green, but the Year before they withered?</p>
            <p>Againſt this Reflection, I know but one Inſtance they have to object: and that is the Hints <hi>Mene-Tekel</hi> gave of King <hi>James</hi>'s Death, a little before the <hi>Abdication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe, but not granting that to be true too, it doth not follow, becauſe once in an Age, among a thouſand falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, one is fulfilled, that they are true Prophets; more than that the <hi>Devil</hi> is not a Lyer, becauſe he once ſpake truth. The veracity of them both is the ſame, in deſpight of a ſingle Inſtance each have to the contrary. <hi>One Swallow doth not make a Summer.</hi> When Aſtrologers, like the Father of Lyes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly fail, and err in their Predictions, it's to be ſuppoſed that Chance, or ſome other Intelligence, not the Stars, put them ſo rarely into the right. <hi>Children, and Fools ſpeak truth,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93964:23"/>ſaith the Proverb: And the Scriptures tell us, that the Devil himſelf, by the Miraculous Power of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> had ſuch a force put upon his Nature, as to do it once, when he acknowledged our <hi>Saviour</hi> to be the Son of God. Aſtrologers may therefore be allowed to reſemble them in this, as they do in all things elſe; though like common Lyers, they are not to be believed, till their Truth becomes apparent by experience, and that (God wot) will be but ſeldom. If it be a good Argument to prove the Truth of Aſtrology, that ſome Predictions have been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, by the ſame ſort of Logick it's to be proved falſe, becauſe their Divinations are oftener ſo than otherwiſe; as is confeſſed by <hi>Cardan,</hi> and proved by <hi>Picus, Heminga, Gaſſendus, Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> and many others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mene-Tekel</hi> not only got the Author a great Name, but patcht up the decayed Credit of Aſtrology among the Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, becauſe they could not ſee the Spirit by which he Divin'd. But wiſer Men knew he Predicted by Intelligence with the <hi>Contrivers,</hi> not the <hi>Planets.</hi> The Stars that preſignified it to him, dwelt on Earth, not in the Twelve Houſes of Heaven. And they perhaps did not err, who lookt on the whole thing as a Political Device to diſpoſe the Minds of People to that great Change: We all know that he fail'd in the Death of King <hi>James,</hi> the Employment of his Gallows, and many other particulars: And he that knew the great, and univerſal diſcontent in the Nation, at the Management of Affairs under that unfortunate Prince, and how many were engaged to dethrone him, might without Aſtrology foreſee as much as he. I know a <hi>Great Man</hi> who (although no Conjurer) told me as much, and as ſoon, as <hi>Mene-Tekel</hi> did, of that buſineſs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Laplanders</hi> may eaſily foretel a Storm they are about to raiſe, and he that is the Inſtrument of Miſchief, is beſt able to Predict the conſequence of his Deſign: Like thoſe Skilful <hi>Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners</hi> Naturaliſts<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theophr.</hi> Hiſt Plant. l. 9 c. 6. <hi>Boyl</hi> Nat. Phil. p. 264. <hi>Medela Medie</hi> p. 103. <hi>Ramſey</hi> of Poyſon p. 10.</note> and Travellers tell us of, who contrive the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Doſe ſo, that the <hi>Victim</hi> ſhall not die in many Years after taking it, and then not miſs an hour. Such a <hi>Pandora</hi> may eaſily turn Aſtrologer, as well as Poyſoner; and foretel the time of the Patient's <hi>Exit,</hi> more certainly than any Genethliac by the Nativity.</p>
            <p>We are told that the <hi>Indians</hi> have, and <hi>Caeſar Borgia</hi> had this pernicious Skill: and it's ſuſpected that there were in <hi>England</hi> ſome, who, without Aſtrology, knew, many days before King
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93964:23"/>
               <hi>Charles</hi> was ſick, when he ſhould die. By the ſame way Dr. <hi>Bates, Cromwell</hi>'s Phyſician, became a truer Prophet than <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Goodwin</hi> his Chaplain; the Doſe the one gave being too hard for the Prayers the other made for that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper.</hi> Though they were alike confident, the one of his Death, the other of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery; yet the former went on the ſureſt grounds, as appeared in the Event.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thuanus, Scaliger,</hi> and <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> ſay that <hi>Cardan</hi> loſt his Life to ſave his Credit; for having Predicted the time of his own Death, he ſtarved himſelf to verifie it;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrom.</hi> p. 173. Dr. <hi>More Myſt.</hi> p. 358.</note> or elſe being ſure of his Art, He took that to be his fatal day, and by thoſe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions made it ſo. And I do not want a learned Author to back my belief, that great men have untimely died by ſome Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice of the Aſtrologers, for the ſame reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Domitian</hi> having Decreed to baniſh all the Aſtrologers, they conſpired his Death; and one of them, <hi>Aſcletarion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sueton.</hi> lib. 12. Sect. 15.</note> told him when it ſhould be. The time appointed happening while <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius Tyanaeus</hi> was Diſputing in the Schools at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> he ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſtopt, and cryed out, <hi>well done</hi> Stephanus! <hi>Kill the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant!</hi> And then told the Audience that the Emperor was wounded. This contributed highly to the Fame of that <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor,</hi> although it prov'd him ſuch no more than the Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> or one of the Prieſts who contrived and managed the Revolt of <hi>Portugal,</hi> if they had foretold it.</p>
            <p>A Son of <hi>Noſtradamus</hi> told the Men of <hi>Friuli,</hi> that he was ſent by his Father to premoniſh them of the ruin of their City by Fire ſuch a Night: They believing the <hi>Oracle,</hi> and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing narrowly to prevent the Conflagration, found him, and his Accomplices, ſcattering Fire-Balls in divers parts of the Town.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Hildebrand</hi> was one who Studied, and Practiſed this Art: and yet had ſo little Skill, or Confidence in it, that he hired ſeveral Ruffians to Murther the Emperor <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. at the time he Predicted his Death.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts and Mon.</hi> Vol. 1. p. 199. Vol. 2. p. 170.</note> This we are told by Cardinal <hi>Beno,</hi> of his own Religion. Beſide <hi>Fox</hi> and others of ours, <hi>Ollerius Barcinonenſis,</hi> foretold the Aſſaſſination of <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. of <hi>France</hi> by <hi>Ravaillac,</hi> from a ſecret Intimation of the Deſign, known to ſome Grandees of <hi>Spain,</hi> and others of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> who were no Aſtrologers. The Author of the <hi>Turkiſh Spy</hi> tells us, that <hi>Fr. Corvinus</hi> the famous <hi>Italian</hi> Aſtrologer, the Night before that Murther, ſaid on the top of his Houſe in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93964:24"/>
               <hi>Florence,</hi> That to morrow the greateſt King in <hi>Europe</hi> would be kill'd: But ſays, <hi>the Intelligence he had was from Earth, not Heaven, or the Stars.</hi> And <hi>Merlinus Liberatus</hi> will not allow his Friend <hi>John</hi> to have any other foreſight of the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> his Birth, than by the Tranſactors of that Myſterious Affair, that is by the ſame way and means himſelf knew what he Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in his <hi>Mene-Tekel:</hi> For without the help of <hi>Satan,</hi> or the <hi>Stars,</hi> any one may Predict Events, if they are in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance, or have Intelligence with thoſe that are ſo.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Their Ignorance of their own Affairs, Misfortunes, and Fates before they happen, proves them unable to foretell that of other Men.</hi> Aſtrologers, ſaith <hi>Agrippa,</hi> while they gaze on the Stars for direction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> fall into Ditches, Wells, and Gaols, and like <hi>Thales,</hi> become the Sport, and Deriſion of ſilly Women, and Slaves.
<q>
                  <l>Aſtra tibi Aethereo pandunt ſeſe omnia Vati,</l>
                  <l>Omnibus &amp; quae ſunt fata futura monent.</l>
                  <l>Omnibus aſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor quòd ſe tua publicat, id te</l>
                  <l>Aſtra (licet videant omnia) nulla monent.</l>
               </q> was an Epigram made by Sir <hi>Tho. More;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>R. Caſtro</hi> Med. Polit. l. 2. c. 2.</note> and I fancy our witty <hi>Hudibras</hi> was as ſharp upon <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> and <hi>Wachum</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as the other was in <hi>Latin.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Hudibras,</hi> the Stars determin,</l>
               <l>You are my Priſoners, baſe Vermin.</l>
               <l>Could they not tell you that as well,</l>
               <l>As what I came to know, foretel?</l>
               <l>By this what Cheats you are we find:</l>
               <l>Who in your own Concerns are blind.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Learned Mr. <hi>Purchas</hi> tells us that the Death of <hi>Hagag</hi> a <hi>Sarazen</hi> King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pilgrim,</hi> p. 226.</note> was foretold by an Aſtrologer, who did not foreſee his own; for as ſoon as he made his Prognoſtick of the King, his own Head was ſtruck off.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Chardin</hi> in the Hiſtory of his <hi>Perſian</hi> Voyage,<note place="margin">Page 40. 131. 132. <hi>Appen.</hi> 25.</note> tells us, That <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> are in very great eſteem among that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: And that they alway crown their Kings in the minute they direct. And if after that the King be unhappy, he is crowned again on a new choſen time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cauſin</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Court.</note> as <hi>Solyman</hi> the Third was ſo crowned while he was in that Country. But the Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers often miſtake, and are as often put to Death.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Hen.</hi> 7. underſtanding, that an Aſtrologer had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told the punctual time of his Death, ſent for him, and enquired
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93964:24"/>where he, the Conjurer, ſhould keep his next <hi>Chriſtmas?</hi> He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that he knew not. Then quoth the <hi>King</hi> I do without Aſtrology tell you, it ſhall be in Gaol. And thither he ſent, and kept him long enough to ſee by Experience, that the <hi>King</hi> was a truer Prognoſticator than himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. Galeazus,</hi> Duke of <hi>Milan,</hi> treated another Impudent A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologer with more ſeverity; for having Predicted that he ſhould long ſurvive that Prince, he Ordered the Wretch to be immediately hanged. Such another Story is in the <hi>Anthologia</hi> of <hi>Diophantes</hi> the great Aſtrologer,<note place="margin">Gaſſend.</note> done in Verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gaurichius</hi> did not foreſee by the Stars, that he was to ſuffer on the <hi>Rack;</hi> nor <hi>Cardan</hi> that his Son was to be hanged for Poyſoning his Wife.</p>
            <p>I was perſonally acquainted with Dr. <hi>W. Ramſey,</hi> who pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly boaſted of Skill enough in Aſtrology to foreknow a Mans Fate; particularly whether he were born to die rich,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chr. Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> cap. 6. Sect. 6</note> be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate in Marriage, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and depended ſo much on it, as to aſſure himſelf of great Wealth, and happy Nuptials; who yet died poor, in a Gaol, after he had Marry'd ſuch a Wife as provoked him to write that Satyr againſt Matrimony, called <hi>Conjugium Conjurgium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Beelzebub</hi> of Aſtrologers, <hi>W. Lilly,</hi> was wholly Ignorant of the Reſtauration, when he wrote thoſe Trayterous Libels, which forfeited his Neck to the Gallows.</p>
            <p>Friend <hi>John</hi> was ſo certain that Popery would prevail,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Opus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</hi> p. 85.</note> and eradicate the <hi>Northern Hereſy,</hi> and ſo Ignorant of the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution, that he not only perſuaded a Gentleman to turn <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt</hi> for theſe Reaſons, but embarkt himſelf in that Intereſt; and thereby drew ſuch a Storm on his Head, as he would have avoided, if his Art had given him the leaſt Proſpect of the right way, or had not led him into the wrong.</p>
            <p>Would <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> think you, have undergone the hazard, and trouble of a Voyage to <hi>America,</hi> to <hi>repair a broken Fortune,</hi> if the Stars had let him ſee, that he ſhould have returned no wiſer, nor richer than he went out? Pray ask that Lying Aſtrologer, (who ſo often writes as if Conſcience, and Religion, not <hi>Debt</hi> and <hi>Beggary</hi> drove him thither) whether it was not he that raiſed ſo many Devils, as during his abode there, and ſince, have poſſeſt the choiceſt Saints in <hi>New-England?</hi> To conclude, <hi>All that pack of</hi> Fools, <hi>and</hi> Knaves, <hi>who pretend by Judicial</hi> Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, <hi>to foreſee good and bad fortune, to hit opportunities, and nick
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93964:25"/>lucky minutes, for making things happy, confute themſelves; being, for the moſt part, hated, ſcandalous, little, needy fellows; the very abjects of that fortune, whoſe favours they pretend to foreſee, and manage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Aſtrology <hi>cannot be true, becauſe Men born at one time, and in one Horoſcope, and Conſtellation, meet divers, often contrary Fates:</hi> Kings and Slaves, Lords and Beggars have been born in one minute; Twins begotten at one Coition, and yet of different<note n="*" place="margin">See ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſingular Inſtances of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Fates and Diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny famous <hi>Twins,</hi> in Mr. <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, p. 53.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Dr.</hi> More<hi>'s</hi> Myſt. Iniq. <hi>p. 357.</hi> Heyden, <hi>p. 252.</hi>
               </note> Sexes, Humours and Fortunes. Of Seed thrown into the Ground in one moment, ſome have taken root, ſome been eaten by Birds and Worms, and ſome proved fruitleſs. A Man born at once, by the Rules of Aſtrology, ſhould die all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But contrariwiſe, ſome Men ſurvive their Ears, Noſes, Hands, Feet, Legs, and Arms, many Years. Nor is it ſo in <hi>Genethliacs</hi> only, but in Judicial, and <hi>Horary Aſtrology</hi> alſo. Ships commencing Voyages in one minute, and Mens Journeys in one moment, have had different ſucceſs. If two Men, or more, about to fight a Duel, or run a Race, come in one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to enquire of the Aſtrologer their ſucceſs; by the Rules of that Art, both muſt win, or loſe; conquer, or be conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; becauſe they both put the Queſtion together. So if two, or three Men ride, or run a Race, and in one moment ſtart forth, if Aſtrology were true, they muſt both win, or both loſe; which cannot be.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>The death of</hi> Multitudes <hi>of Men, in one minute, ſome in one moment, in one place, by one cauſe, cannot happen by the Rules of Aſtrology:</hi> Becauſe the Stars never concur to ſuch an Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Fate in ſo many thouſand Nativities,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>W. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh</hi> p. 153.</note> as theirs who fell in the Battel between <hi>Semiramis,</hi> and <hi>Stourobates,</hi> where Four Millions were ſlain on one ſide, beſides the many Thouſands which fell on the other. The Army of <hi>Xerxes,</hi> when they paſs'd the <hi>Helleſpont,</hi> conſiſted of Seventeen Hundred Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> l. 3. cap. 6.</note> the greater part of which fell in the Battels of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tea,</hi> and <hi>Mycale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Scripture</hi> we read of 320000 ſlain at one time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſhua</hi> cap. 11. <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.16.</note> on one ſide; and 500000 at another; beſide the many who periſhed on the ſide of the Vanquiſhers: 180000 <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> died by the hand of an <hi>Angel,</hi> at one time, in the days of <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> Are theſe things accountable by the Rules of <hi>Genethliacal Aſtrology?</hi> If the ſmall diſtance that might be between their Fates, be an Evaſion, What think you of vaſter numbers, who have pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93964:25"/>together in a moment, by one accident? The Hundreds blown up with <hi>Opdam;</hi> the Thouſands ſwallowed by the Earth with <hi>Corah,</hi> &amp;c. in the Wilderneſs; and of late in <hi>Jamaica, Sicilia,</hi> &amp;c. or the Inundations of <hi>Deucalion, Holland,</hi> &amp;c. or the Flood of <hi>Noah?</hi> Can their Fates be found Predicted by ſo long a Conſpiracy of the Stars, as muſt be in the many days, in which thoſe Multitudes of Nations were born? Can the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Births of ſo many <hi>Myriads</hi> of Men, have in the compaſs of an Hundred Years, ſuch conſpiring Horoſcopes, as ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine them all to one ſort of Death, and <hi>puncto</hi> of dying? Can the Heaven for ſo many millions of minutes, as theſe Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes were Born in, have ſo conſtant and agreeable an Aſpect,<note place="margin">Dr. More<hi>'s</hi> Myſt. p. <hi>357.</hi>
               </note> as there muſt be, if Aſtrology be true, to determine the Fate of ſuch infinite Numbers, to the ſame Numerical time, and Identical manner of Death? I call them infinite Numbers, believing, with Sir <hi>Tho. Brown,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſeud. Ep.</hi> l. 6. c 6.</note> that the World was then as full of People as now.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>If the Stars Influence, or Coeleſtial Conſtellations beget ſuch Accidents as occur on Earth; How comes it, that when the like</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſcopes <hi>recurr, as were at the Geneſis of</hi> Alexander, Caeſar, <hi>or</hi> Judas, <hi>Men moſt famous for Piety, Art, Valour, Poetry,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or infamous for Wickedneſs, have not been again produced?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. If Human Actions be directed by the Stars, Whence is it that National Cuſtoms of <hi>Food, Cloathes, Religion, Marriages, Diſeaſes, Languages, Laws, Tempers, Colours, Conſtitutions,</hi> &amp;c. come to be peculiar, and conſtant to each Kingdom, when the Influence of Heaven on them, is ſo various? The Heavens change, but the People do not. The People of the greateſt part of the Earth are black, the Wind blows conſtantly one way for Eleven Months of the Year; and the Weather, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that time, <hi>Serene,</hi> without Rain, or Storms: And in that Month varieth, with Tempeſts, and great Showers, or Floods from the Sky. This cannot be from the Stars.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The <hi>Aſtronomancers</hi> talk much of the untimely death of <hi>Picus,</hi> and other Writers againſt their Art, as if it were a Revenge the Stars took on ſuch as derogated from their Dominion: But have they not as much Power to Prevent, as to Revenge ſuch Injuries done their Sovereignties? If all our Actions, or thoſe only of Importance be directed by the Stars; Is it not abſurd to ſuppoſe they ſhould inſpire ſo many great <hi>Fathers, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93964:26"/>Divines,</hi> and the moſt <hi>Learned</hi> Men the World hath owned, with Diſpoſition, or Ability to write againſt them; and ſingle out one or two of them to puniſh; and ſuffer ſo many others, who have as much, or more, affronted their Deities, to eſcape, and proſper?</p>
            <p n="14">14. <hi>The Exclamations made by Men Great, Learned, and Good,</hi> ſome of which have ſtudied your Art to the bottom, gives great reaſon to think it <hi>Fallacious,</hi> and <hi>Wicked.</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtin, Calvin, Perkins, Briggs, Heminga,</hi> Dr. <hi>Humes, Angelis,</hi> and other Divines: <hi>Picus Mirandula, J. Scaliger, C. Agrippa,</hi> Mr. <hi>Freke,</hi> and many Philoſophers, who were Famous <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> call it <hi>Fallacious, Fabulous, Ridiculous, and Vain;</hi> and its Profeſſors <hi>Cheats, Impious, Factious,</hi> and Dangerous in a Commonwealth; Beſide, Multitudes of the moſt Famous Men of all Learned Profeſſions, who have decryed it as a Deluſion, and expoſed the Vanity, Falſity, and Wickedneſs of ſuch as pretend to Prognoſticate by it.</p>
            <p>Among the <hi>Fathers</hi> not one of them was for it, but <hi>Origen. Tertullian</hi> ſaid that it was invented by the Devil, and he baniſh'd Heaven for it. St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> calls it wicked, and vain. St. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> call it <hi>fooliſh Madneſs, invented by Satan.</hi> So doth St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, Euſebius, Lactantius,</hi> St. <hi>Gregory;</hi> and almoſt all the Fathers wrote againſt it. <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> calls it a Deviliſh Art. <hi>Luther, Junius, Melancton, P. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, Gualterus, Willit, Cauſin, B. Charlton, M. Chambers,</hi> Mr. <hi>Purchas,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Taylor, Stillingfleet,</hi> Dr. <hi>More,</hi> Mr. <hi>Giree, Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Gattaker, Gale, Crow,</hi> have all exploded it, as contrary to Truth, Religion, and the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>Being invented by the Devil, and practiſed by his Diſciples, in oppoſition to Religion, and Godlineſs,</hi> it diſpoſeth the Minds of Men to Idolatry, and Atheiſm; attributing to the Creature, the Power of the Creator; or believing them really Gods, as the Heathens did. It takes off our dependance on God; ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Prayer uſeleſs; deſtroyeth Free Will; makes us of free <hi>Agents,</hi> paſſive <hi>Patients.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith more than once, that it came from Heaven, but was brought from thence by the Fallen Angels; and we all know what the greateſt Aſſertors of it in former Ages were: <hi>Pharaoh, Nebuchadnezzar, Nero, Julian, Manaſſes, Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus</hi> the Tyrant, <hi>Jannes,</hi> and <hi>Jambres, Elymas</hi> the Sorcerer, <hi>Albumazer, Caracalla, Menander, Saturninus, Hildebrand, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates, Priſcillianus, Porphyry,</hi> &amp;c. who were all of them <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93964:26"/>of Hell,</hi> and Lovers of Aſtrology. It muſt needs be ſo;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vaninus,</hi> the great Advocate for Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, died a profeſs'd Atheiſt. <hi>Vide Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Tent. de deo Diſp.</hi> 1. Sect. 26.</note> for the <hi>Devil</hi> is the Guardian Angel of their Art; and I'll tell you how they came by him. In the Pontificate of ſome ſuch Holy Father as <hi>Gregory</hi> 7. a Lover of this Black Art, one of the Tribe craved of his Holineſs a Protector or Patron Saint for <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> like as other Arts had. The Good <hi>Pontiff</hi> willing to oblige a Faculty he loved well, gave him the Choice of all in St. <hi>Peters.</hi> The humble Servant of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> depending upon the Direction of good Stars to a good Angel, went to the Choice <hi>hoodwinkt;</hi> and groping among the Images, the firſt he laid hand on, was that of the <hi>Devil</hi> in Combat with St. <hi>Michael.</hi> Had he choſen with open Eyes he could not have met a ſitter Protector for ſo Diabolical an Art.</p>
            <p>It's aſſerted by Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> that it leads Chriſtians to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,<note place="margin">On <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 47. and <hi>Jerem.</hi> 10.</note> by attributing Divine Power to Planets, making them not only the occaſion of Good, and Evil in general, but extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates, and ſubjects the Power of <hi>Religion, Miracles, Efficacy</hi> of Prayer, all <hi>Piety,</hi> and the ſtate of <hi>future Life,</hi> to depend on the Stars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Venus,</hi> they ſay, gives the Felicities of this Life, and <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> of that to come: for when he reigns, the Native ſhall be eternally happy. When <hi>Saturn</hi> is placed in <hi>Leo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lex Judai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca eſt à <hi>Saturno;</hi> Chriſtiana à <hi>Jove</hi> &amp; <hi>Mercurio;</hi> Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica à <hi>Sole</hi> &amp; <hi>Marte,</hi> &amp; Idololatria, à <hi>Luna</hi> &amp; <hi>Marte. Card.</hi>
               </note> the Body ſhall live long, and the Soul for ever. He that prayeth to <hi>God</hi> when the <hi>Moon</hi> with the Head of the <hi>Dragon</hi> is joyned to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> ſhall obtain whatever he asketh. He that's placed under <hi>Mars</hi> in the ninth Houſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall be able to caſt out <hi>Devils.</hi> A Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet muſt be born, if in <hi>Gemini, &amp;c.</hi> In ſhort, <hi>The Gift of Prophecy, Power of Religion, Secrets of Conſcience, Command over Devils, Vertue of Miracles, Efficacy of Prayer, Future State,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are all made by theſe Men to depend on the Stars;</hi> Vouchſafed by them, and to be known from them. The <hi>Flood, Moſes</hi>'s Law, <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Birth and Death are ſaid to be the Effects of their Influences, by thoſe Blaſphemous Aſtrologers, ſaith that Great Proteſtant Father. Theſe, and ſuch horrible Opinions do they hold, who pretend to Chriſtianity: But how unworthy of that Name, let all ſober Men of that Religion judge.</p>
            <p>Some of them have been ſo daringly Blaſphemous, as to write, That <hi>Chriſt was famous for ſo many Miracles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>More</hi>'s <hi>Myſt. God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs,</hi> p. 337.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe He was born while</hi> Saturn <hi>and</hi> Gemini, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That He Diſputed with the Doctors ſo Young, becauſe <hi>Jupiter,</hi> &amp;c. His many Travels, often Weeping, never Laughing, the prevalency of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93964:27"/>his Goſpel, are all attributed to the Poſition of the Planets at his Birth,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>More.</hi> againſt <hi>J. B.</hi> p 158 <hi>Notes</hi> c. 34. p. 148. <hi>Myſt God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs</hi> p. 338. Page 49.</note> by ſuch pretended Chriſtian Aſtrologers, as <hi>Mater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Cardan, R. Bacon, A. Villa Nova, Vaninus,</hi> Card. <hi>Alliacenſis, Priſcillianus,</hi> and many others. But Mr. <hi>Gregory</hi> and Dr. <hi>More</hi> ſhow, that they cannot agree in what Sign he was born: It's true, that an extraordinary Star led the <hi>Magi</hi> to the place where he lay; and our Star-gazers don't ſpare to tell us of it; and endeavour to perſuade us, that thoſe Wiſe Men were <hi>Aſtrologers:</hi> But that's confuted over, and over, by Mr. <hi>Gregory,</hi> who hath pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed a Scheme of that Great Nativity.</p>
            <p>But beſides thoſe Powers which they ſo Blaſphemouſly attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Stars, over the Actions, and Paſſion of <hi>Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, they ruin the true Notion of <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Providence,</hi> whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy <hi>Free Will,</hi> in the moſt minute things; and leave us not ſo much liberty of Choice, as the moſt rigid <hi>Predeſtinators</hi> have done; but ſix us under ſuch a fatal Neceſſity, as the <hi>Hobbiſts</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts</hi> do.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Chr. Heyden,</hi> the Great Advocate of Aſtrology, affirms, That the Efficacy of the Stars cannot be fruſtrate without a Miracle:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Row and</hi> againſt <hi>W. R.</hi> p. 136.</note> Where is then the Providence of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Free Will?</hi> To what end is Prayer, and ſecond means, if there be ſuch an abſolute Deſtiny, and irreſiſtible Influence? We are not free Agents, but, like <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Puppits, act and ſpeak as <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> or <hi>Mars</hi> pleaſe to conſtrain us:<note place="margin">De Civit. De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>lib. 5.</hi>
               </note> Or (as the Aſtrologer ſpoken of by St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi>) <hi>It's not we that Luſted, but</hi> Venus: <hi>Not we that Slew, but</hi> Mars: <hi>Not we that Stole, but</hi> Mercury: <hi>Not God that helpt, but</hi> Jupiter: And ſo Free-born Man is made a <hi>Star-born Slave.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In excuſe of theſe Conſequences, the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> when put to it, are ſometimes ſo ſenſeleſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>J. B.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Dr. <hi>More,</hi> p. 93. <hi>More</hi>'s <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> p. 122, 123.</note> as to confound <hi>Fortune,</hi> which is <hi>Chance;</hi> and <hi>Fate,</hi> which is determined, and inevitable. And to help their Cauſe from thoſe preſſing Difficulties, which incumber it, with worſe: For to avoid the foreſaid Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they deny the Stars Neceſſitate, and allow them only to Diſpoſe. They Incline, but do not Force: Therefore Wiſe Men rule the Stars.<note place="margin">Sapiens do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minabitur Aſtris.</note> But what is <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> if that be true? How can he Predict that, which every Wiſe Man may defeat, and none but Fools are ſure to verifie? Can he tell what will come to paſs, if every Wiſe Man hath Power to fruſtrate the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction?</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:93964:27"/>
            <p>Beſide all this miſchief Aſtrology doth to Religion and Chriſtianity, it's an Art not only near of Kin to <hi>Witchcraft,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. Civit. Dei</hi> lib. 5. c. 7. Dr. <hi>More ubi ſup.</hi> p 358. <hi>Vind.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Chambers</hi> cap. 19.</note> and <hi>Magick,</hi> but leads Men into it, as divers, who have eſcaped the Snare, acknowledge. Sir <hi>Ch. Heyden</hi> (their Zealous Advocate) confeſſeth that <hi>Necromancy is often palliated under the pretence of Aſtrology.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Butler</hi> the <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> in the Preface to his <hi>Hagiaſtrologia,</hi> page 24. confeſſeth, That without the Heavenly and Supernatural Wiſdom, Aſtrological Skill would become rank Poyſon to the <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> as being ſuch a thing as would lead him to the Devil, ſooner than to God; and draw him into Sorcery, and other evil Arts, whereby they would be entangled with Diabolical Familiarities ere they are aware, even as are Witches and Conjurers. See more the like in the Book it ſelf, p. 35. and 38.</p>
            <p>When Men become greedy of knowing things before hand, they bind themſelves Apprentices to the <hi>Devil</hi>'s Black Art: For he, who is never wanting to gratifie wicked deſires, helps them to foreſee by a worſe Art than Aſtrology, though that be bad enough, what they deſire to know. Thus <hi>Julian, Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debrand,</hi> and many more, proceeded from Aſtrology to <hi>Necro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy,</hi> and ſuch abominable Diabolical Practices, as would make a Man tremble to read. After the death of the Apoſtate, there were found in <hi>Antioch</hi> ſundry Heads, and Carcaſſes of Men, Women, and Children, barbarouſly ſlain for Divination, and Sacrificed to the informing <hi>Daemon.</hi> In one Temple he acted ſuch execrable things, as he ſtrove to conceal, forbiding any one to open it beſide himſelf: But after his death, they found among many other cruel Effects of his helliſh Curioſity, a Woman hanging by the Hair of her Head, her Hands cut off, her Belly ript up, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to vaticinate his <hi>Perſian</hi> Victory. This not only ſhows the danger of thoſe unreaſonable Deſires, which put Men on uſe of Aſtrology; but the defect of it: <hi>For if the Stars could foretel Men things to come, they would not go to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil for more Skill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Art being of ſo Deviliſh an Original, ſo hurtful to Religion, Providence, Dependance on <hi>God,</hi> and all <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Duties;</hi> leading Men to <hi>Atheiſm, Idolatry, Blaſphemy, Witchcraft, Magick, Murther,</hi> and cruel <hi>Butchery;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Picus Mir.</hi> p. 434. Againſt Dr <hi>Humes.</hi> cap. 31.</note> how great is the Impudence of thoſe Men, who publickly call it <hi>an Art uſeful to Religion?</hi> As <hi>R. Bacon,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Alliacenſis,</hi> and others have done. A Divine Study, as <hi>Ramſey</hi> calls it; the only Way, and Path that leads to <hi>God,</hi> as others ſay; an Art near
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93964:28"/>of Kin to <hi>Divinity,</hi> as<note n="*" place="margin">Preface to Sir <hi>G. W.</hi> Works, and in his <hi>Excellency of Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> p. 15. <hi>J. Butler</hi> againſt Dr. <hi>More.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>J. Gadbury</hi> hath the confidence more than once to affirm; and a moſt Sacred and Divine Study, as one who calls himſelf a Miniſter of the Goſpel ſaith; when nothing is more deſtructive thereof, and different from it, leſs like it, leſs a Friend, or of leſs Affinity to it than that? To falſe Prophets, and lying Spirits, the Relation and Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of thoſe Deluders cannot be deny'd; we ſaw them but the other day in theſe miſerable Nations: <hi>James Naylor, O. Sedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, Mary Cary, Hannab Tapnel,</hi> and other <hi>Enthuſiaſtick, Hyſterical Millennaries,</hi> who Propheſy'd, as <hi>Lilly</hi> and <hi>Culpeper</hi> Prognoſticated; as <hi>Goodwin, Bond,</hi> and <hi>H. Peters</hi> Preacht, or Scribled; and all as far from Truth, as the Infernal Author of the Black Art is from an Angel of Light.</p>
            <p n="16">16. They have the boldneſs to affirm, that their Art is of ſuch abſolute neceſſity in curing Diſeaſes, that not a Plant can be gathered; a Medicine compounded, or adminiſtred; an Operation made, or a Judgment given without it. But this pretence is alſo vain, like all the reſt, being an old Maggot, bred in ſome ancient Phyſicians Brains, and would have long ſince died, if it had not been nouriſh'd by a few Modern Luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks — A Purge, ſay they, is not to be given while the <hi>Moon</hi> is in <hi>Aries,</hi> or <hi>Taurus,</hi> becauſe they being Signs of ſuch Creatures as chew the Cudd, the Patient will therefore Nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, and Vomit it up again. Such ſottiſh, and ridiculous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do they give for the uſe of <hi>Aſtrology</hi> in the Art of Healing.</p>
            <p>But all the moſt Famous, and Learned Phyſicians of later Ages, from ſounder Principles of Philoſophy, underſtand bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and either explode this vain Art, and reject it, or take no notice of it in their approved Writings, nor in their Practice.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vanit.</hi> cap. 30, 31.</note>
               <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> was a Phyſician, and had been an <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:</hi> He tells us, it's ſo far from being uſeful in Phyſick, that <hi>it renders uſeleſs all the endeavours of the Phyſician, and excuſeth the miſchievous doings of Quacks, and Empiricks,</hi> which probably is the chief Reaſon why it's ſo much in eſteem among them. <hi>It depriveth an able Doctor of the Credit due to his ſucceſsful Skill, by attributing the fate of the Sick,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to Coeleſtial Influences.</hi> In ſhort, he calls it a <hi>ridiculous, and groundleſs figment:</hi> And its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors <hi>Cheats, Knaves, Fools, Rebels, Doctors of Falſhood, Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. Falloſius, Eraſtus, Lemnius, Geſner, Ficinius, Valleriolus, Fuchſius, Monardus, Fr. Valeſius, R. à Caſtro. Helmont, Diemer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broek,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:93964:28"/>Dr. <hi>Brown, Witty, Sydenham, Trew,</hi> have written againſt it Some of them ſay, That <hi>neither Men nor Devils can foretel any thing by the Stars.</hi> All of them decry its uſe in Phyſick. And <hi>Sidrophel</hi> himſelf (pardon me for naming him among ſuch Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies) in the Preface to his Tranſlation of <hi>Dolaeus</hi>'s Syſtem, not only leaves it out from among the needful Qualifications of a Phyſician, but hath lately put a <hi>French</hi> Author of the <hi>Pox</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 123. <hi>Probl.</hi> 8.</note> who explodes, and ridicules it as much as any Man.</p>
            <p>In Practice, the moſt Eminent for Skill, buſineſs and ſucceſs, ſlight and diſregard it. And they who have obſerved its Rules, have been convinced by Experience that it ſignifieth nothing. We find no notice of it in the Methods of <hi>Sennertus, Riverius, Willis, Sydenham,</hi> or the moſt Celebrated <hi>Practicers</hi> now alive. And were there nothing to ſhow it a Nullity in the Art of Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the Infamy, Poverty, unſucceſsful attempts of ſuch as pretend to act by it, is demonſtration enough.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Aſtrology, <hi>and Prognoſticating by the Stars, is condemned in</hi> Scripture, <hi>and forbidden by the Mouth of God.</hi> See <hi>Deuteron.</hi> XVIII. 10, 14, 15. <hi>&amp;c. Iſaiah</hi> XLIV. 25. XLVII. 13, 14. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> X. 2. <hi>Acts</hi> XIX. 19. Add to them <hi>Pſalm</hi> CXXXIV. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> XLI. 23. <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> VIII. 7. X. 14. 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> II. 11. and conſider the II. IV. and V. Chapters of <hi>Daniel,</hi> how the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> relying on theſe cheating Aſtrologers, had been deluded by them, and upbraids their Ignorance and Frauds.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Chr. Heyden, Ramſey,</hi> and others endeavour to elude the force of theſe Scriptures; but beſide current Commentators, Dr. <hi>Holmes,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rowland,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gattaker,</hi> and many particular Divines, have proved them fully to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="18">18. Beſides the Holy Oracles of <hi>God,</hi> the Venerable Writings of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and the Learned Arguments of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Aſtrology; the moſt Eminent <hi>Politicians, Stateſmen, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians, Lawyers,</hi> and <hi>Philoſophers</hi> have writ of it with great Contempt and Deteſtation: <hi>Tacitus</hi> in his <hi>Annals</hi> and <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> often ſpeaks of the Miſchiefs they did; and for which they were ſeveral times baniſhed <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Rome. They are,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a ſort of Men falſe to Government, and all that truſt them. Seneca</hi> derides them, <hi>Plutarch</hi> cenſures them, <hi>Cicero</hi> wrote largely againſt them. Alſo<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> in many places relates the Treachery of their Practices, and falſity of their Art. <hi>Nat. Hiſt.</hi> lib. 7. c. 49. lib. 18. c. 23. lib 30. c. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Picus</hi> Lord of <hi>Mirandula,</hi> a Man
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93964:29"/>of high Birth, and great Learning, whom <hi>Scaliger</hi> call'd <hi>the Monſter of his Age;</hi> and <hi>Naudaeus</hi> the <hi>Phoenix</hi> of all great Wits, wrote 200 Years ſince 12 ſuch Invincible Books againſt <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> as not only purchaſed him the Name of <hi>Flagellum Aſtrologorum,</hi> but ſo muzled them all, that not one hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared able to Anſwer him.</p>
            <p>He proves <hi>Aſtrology</hi> to be <hi>an Art invented by the Devil, abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheth all Religion, Philoſophy, Phyſick, Law,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of great miſchief to Mankind, deſtroys the uſe of</hi> Faith, <hi>leſſens the Reverence of</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, <hi>deſtroyes Divine</hi> Providence, <hi>Patronizeth</hi> Sin, <hi>excuſeth Vice as coming from Heaven, defiles and ſubverts all good Arts; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the cauſes of things from Reaſon, to Fables; abrogating all Rules of Human Providence,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Page 183.</note>Sir <hi>Tho. More</hi> makes his <hi>Eutopians</hi> deſpiſe and laugh at them. <hi>R. à Caſtro</hi> tells us he was the Author of that Lampoon againſt them, <hi>Aſtratibi AEthereo pandunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>C. Agrippa</hi> treats them with great Scorn and Deriſion, and expoſeth their Art as a Deluſion, and great Cheat. My Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> not inferior to the beſt of theſe for Learning, ſaith, That <hi>Aſtrology</hi> hath no grounds,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſlaur. Mag.</hi> lib. 3. c. 4. page 3. and <hi>Eſſay.</hi> 35.; <hi>Eſſay</hi> l. 1. c. 4.</note> nor ſoundneſs, and ſuch as Practiſe it, no Honeſty, or Senſe. Their Perſons are deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (ſaith he) but their Practices dangerous. They are Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, who have done great Miſchief; and therefore ſo many Laws have been made to ſuppreſs them. <hi>M. Montaigne,</hi> that Noble <hi>French</hi> Author, tells us, The Art ought to be abhorred by all good Chriſtians, having done much Miſchief, though in it ſelf as inſignificant as a Dream.</p>
            <p>The Learned K. <hi>James</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Daemono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. <hi>l. 1. c. 5.</hi> Verit. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. <hi>l. 4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Judicial Aſtrology</hi> is learnt in the Devil's School. An Art not lawful to Practiſe or be truſted in by Chriſtians, having no ground of Natural Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Both the <hi>Scaligers</hi> (Prodigies of Learning) writ againſt it. The Father againſt <hi>Cardan,</hi> and the Son calls it a Practice without Foundation, contrary to Religion, and Philoſophy, &amp;c. <hi>Praef. Molin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Argenis</hi> l. 2.</note> So ſaith the Famous <hi>J. Barclay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>H. Grotius</hi> (whoſe greateſt Enemies Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>) allowed to be Wiſe above the pitch of Human Nature, and incomparable in all Human Learning, derides <hi>Aſtrology</hi> as an <hi>Art</hi> without agreeing Rules, having <hi>nothing in it certain, but uncertainty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> on St. <hi>Auguſt. Civit. Dei,</hi> our Learned <hi>Savil</hi> in his Notes on <hi>Tacitus,</hi> and others call it, <hi>an Art that teacheth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93964:29"/>Knaves to cheat Honeſt Men.</hi> And <hi>J. Milton</hi> in his <hi>Figure-Caſter</hi> Ridicules it with much Wit, and Confutes it with no leſs Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is an Art that teacheth Aſtrologers to Lye as often as they ſpeak.</hi> Our Ingenious, Learned <hi>Feliham</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> can for bear laughing when they meet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve</hi> 96.</note> to think how they gull the People with ſuch a Fallacy, and Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as is impoſſible to be true. And Mr. <hi>Freke</hi> the <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> calls it <hi>Madneſs, Folly, Deluſion, an Irrational, groundleſs Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture, impoſſible to be true.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſſay</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3. &amp;c.</note> And by Experience found to be the Devil's Lure, to draw Men into <hi>Neoromancy.</hi> What ſhall I ſay more! The Noble <hi>Picus</hi> in his two firſt Books againſt them, hath ſhown at large how much the Learned Writers to his time decryed and wrote againſt this Wicked, Senſeleſs Art. And I have proved that the moſt Eminent Authors ſince, of all ſorts, have done the ſame, and hiſs'd it off the Stage; to whom may be added <hi>Des Cartes, Rohault,</hi> and all the new <hi>French Philoſophers,</hi> beſide our Learned <hi>Athenians.</hi> I might teaze them with <hi>Lucian Juvenal, Quevedo, Hudebraſs, Poor Robin,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wilſon</hi>'s Witty <hi>Play</hi> called the <hi>Cheats,</hi> and others, who with ſharp Wit and keen Satyr, expoſe them in their true Shapes and Colours. (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee Sir <hi>Roger L'Strange</hi>'s Fables, and the <hi>Turkiſh Spye.</hi>) But I muſt haſten the Matter off my Hands, and will ſhut up my Evidence againſt them with one of their own Advocates, <hi>Ramſey,</hi> who was, like <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> a buſy <hi>Scribler,</hi> an Empty <hi>Phyſician,</hi> and an Ignorant <hi>Star-Cazer.</hi> This Man tells the King, That the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Practicers of <hi>Aſtrology</hi> deceived his People of their Money, Lives, and Loyalty, and that <hi>London</hi> abounded with ſuch Ideots, Cheats, and Illiterate Impoſtors, as himſelf was, and <hi>Sidrophel</hi> continueth to be.</p>
            <p>There is much more to be ſaid againſt this vain <hi>Art,</hi> to prove it falſe and built on nothing: As the want of knowing the exact Longitude of the Place, which is both neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and impoſis;ible: So is the moment of the <hi>Geneſis,</hi> Queſtion, or Action to be judged of, and conſequently leave their Erections to meer Chance; and then it's 10000 to one, as Dr. <hi>More</hi> ſaith, but that it prove falſe. <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> affirms, That if there be any thing to be judged by <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> the <hi>Artiſt</hi> muſt know the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe moment of the <hi>Sun</hi>'s being in a <hi>Cardinal Sign;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. p. 728.</note> Yet ſure I am, ſaith he, that there are no Tables, or <hi>Ephemerides</hi> extant that can teach the Time by ſix hours. Thoſe of <hi>Tycho</hi> come neareſt Truth, and yet are wide from it.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:93964:30"/>
            <p>My laſt Argument againſt <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> and their pretended <hi>Art</hi> is, That <hi>in all Ages, and moſt Governments, they have been pernicious to the</hi> Commonwealth, <hi>and Enemies to the Publick</hi> Peace. And for that Reaſon ſo many Laws have been made againſt them, not only abroad, as <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> tell us, but in our own Nation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.14 33.5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 15.23. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2.3.4. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.15.</note> as may be ſeen in the <hi>Statute Book, Beſide their Frauds, and Cozening Practices</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aggrippa, Montaigne,</hi> and <hi>Bacon</hi>) <hi>on the Common People, they are Authors of much miſchief to the State, drawing Credulous People to their ruin, and cauſing among Nations moſt cruel Wars and Sedition: No ſort of Men being more pernicious to a Commonwealth, than thoſe who undertake to Prognoſticate by the Stars, or any other way of Divination, and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Prophecies about.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I urge this laſt of all, becauſe it's ſo pat to the great Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection I have againſt <hi>Sidrophel.</hi> For he ſeems to verify this Cenſure, and to be deſigning by his falſe <hi>Art,</hi> to ſubvert the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Frame of our <hi>Engliſh Government</hi> in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> by making the People believe Heaven hath decreed it ſhall be changed into that of a Neighbouring Country.</p>
            <p>That ſuch effects have been the conſequents of ſuch <hi>Fanatick Enthuſiaſtick Dreams,</hi> I will prove by a few, out of many, Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Socrat.</hi> lib. 7. <hi>Sozom.</hi> lib. 8. <hi>Niceph.</hi> lib. 13.</note>
               <hi>Iſdegerdes</hi> the <hi>Perſian King</hi> was ſo diſturbed by the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> that he decimated them. <hi>Valerius Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus</hi> being overthrown by <hi>Licinius,</hi> contrary to the Predictions of the <hi>Star-Diviners,</hi> who had betrayed him with falſe aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Succeſs, He put them all to death. Thus they deluded <hi>Pompey, Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Craſſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Thucydides Plutarc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Nicias</hi> the <hi>Athenian,</hi> was perſuaded by them to keep his Fleet in the Haven; the ſame Night the <hi>Syracuſians</hi> ſurprized them all. <hi>Plutarch, Tacitus, Suetonius,</hi> &amp;c. ſay that <hi>Otho</hi> was induced to the Murther of <hi>Galba</hi> by the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Magoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 346.</note> who told him he was to ſucceed him in the Imperial Throne. And by the ſame way <hi>Stephanus</hi> was prompted to Aſſaſſinate <hi>Domitian. Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſis</hi> was Murthered by two <hi>Aſtrologers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> to obtain his Ambitious aim, ſuborned them to encourage the <hi>Athenians</hi> to a fatal War with <hi>Sicily.</hi> Many Aſtrologers combined to dethrone <hi>Valens,</hi> and ſet up <hi>Theodorus</hi> a <hi>Pagan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wieri prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtig,</hi> c. 10. p. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> by pretending they found his Name prenoted by the Stars; but the <hi>Emperor</hi> not only ſlew thoſe Trayterous Diviners, but, as the Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſay, all thoſe whoſe Names began with <hi>Theod.</hi> that he
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:93964:30"/>might be ſure to baffle their Prediction. By ſuch Men, and encouragement from the Stars, it was that <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Younger was murthered. <hi>Libo Denſius,</hi> encouraged by <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius Catus,</hi> to make Inſurrection againſt <hi>Tiberius,</hi> in confidence of ſucceſs by <hi>Aſtrological</hi> Prediction, was defeated, and then ſlew himſelf; and ſuch was the Foundation of <hi>Catiline</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy.</p>
            <p>The Story of <hi>Caracalla</hi> is very famous. He, while in <hi>Meſopota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> being Jealous of a Plot againſt him, ſent to the <hi>Roman</hi> Aſtrologers to be informed. They accuſed <hi>Macrinus,</hi> his faithful Praefect, of a Conſpiracy, which nothing but his Death could fruſtrate. This Anſwer coming while the Emperor was intent on ſome ſport, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> gave it <hi>Macrinus</hi> to read; and he finding his innocent Life in danger, by this trick of the Aſtrologers, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured it by the murther of <hi>Caracalla,</hi> of which he had not thought before.</p>
            <p>Such <hi>Diviners</hi> had aſſured the Wife of <hi>Pheroras,</hi> that the Line of <hi>Herod</hi> would extinguiſh,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſeph. Antiq.</hi> lib. 17. cap. 3.</note> and her Husband ſucceed to the Crown. They, to aſſiſt their Stars, and work out their own good Fortune, conſpired againſt the King's Life, and loſt all their own by the ſtroke of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomet</hi> the III. had a Rebellion raiſed againſt him by the Aſtrologers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Purchas Pilgr.</hi> p. 276.</note> Predicting that his Son ſhould overcome and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him: But all proved falſe, and the Son, Aſtrologers, and Rebels were ſlain.</p>
            <p>The D. of <hi>Viſco</hi> was by the Aſtrologers aſſured of his having the Crown of <hi>Portugal</hi> after the Death of <hi>Don Juan el Grandes:</hi> But impatient of gaining it, he Rebelled againſt him a firſt time, and was both Defeated, and Pardoned. Upon a ſecond Attempt, he fell by the Hand he would have untimely ruined.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſſay</hi> 11. lib. 1,</note> 
               <hi>M. Montaigne</hi> tells us, that the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Saluza,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> in the Days of <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, having all imaginable Advantage againſt the Enemy, was, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo terrified by the Aſtrologers, who had Predicted the Succeſs of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, and the Ruin of <hi>France,</hi> that he baſely Revolted, to his own perpetual Infamy and Ruin.</p>
            <p>We will leave Foreign Inſtances of the miſchief done by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers to Princes, and Kingdoms; and now take a view of what hath been wrought by them in our own Country, ſo long famous for giving Credit to ſuch <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> as will appear by the following Hiſtory.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:93964:31"/>
            <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> have been often thus betrayed into <hi>Rebellion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Speed</hi> p. 672.</note> and the Murther of <hi>Kings.</hi> The Earl of <hi>Athol</hi> was prompted to Conſpire againſt <hi>James</hi> I. by their aſſuring him, that he ſhould be Crowned in that Kingdom: and true it was, for the King underſtanding what inſtigated him to Rebel, he cauſed a Crown of red hot Iron to be put on his Head, by which, and ſome other Tortures, he ended his wretched Life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fuller</hi>'s Worthies of <hi>Wales,</hi> p. 19.</note>The <hi>Welch</hi> have a Saying publiſhed by one of them, that <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide</hi> God, <hi>there is no Diviner;</hi> and yet ſo far purſued their hard Fate, that by the Inſtigations of thoſe Aſtrological <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefeaus,</hi> who had poſſeſs'd Prince <hi>Leolin,</hi> that He ſhould wear the Crown of <hi>Brutus;</hi> he firſt refuſed to attend the Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Edward</hi> I. then Rebell'd againſt him, and Invaded <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but was Vanquiſh'd and Slain, His whole Family extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated, His Title annexed to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Welch</hi> ſubjected to its Laws ever ſince.</p>
            <p>Afterward in the Days of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. <hi>Owen Glyn Dower Dwy</hi> became inveigled by a Prophecy of <hi>Merlin</hi>'s,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Powel</hi>'s Hiſt. p. 386.</note> (whoſe Name <hi>Lilly</hi> and <hi>Partridge</hi> affect) that the time was come, wherein the <hi>Britains,</hi> by his Aſſiſtance, ſhould recover their Ancient Freedom and Liberty; Rebelled, made War, and were overthrown, and curbed by ſuch Laws, as Dr. <hi>Fuller</hi> compares to thoſe of <hi>Draco,</hi> written in Blood.</p>
            <p>In our part of this Iſle, we find <hi>Peter Pomfret</hi> attempted to raiſe a Commotion againſt King <hi>John,</hi> by buzzing into the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Ears certain Prophecies from the Stars: And in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> VI. by the ſame Device,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi>'s Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi> 6.</note> the People were made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That there ſhould no more Kings Reign in <hi>England;</hi> That all the Nobility ſhould be deſtroyed, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fall into the Hands of four Commoners. A Prophecy much like that of <hi>Sidrophel</hi>'s, but expreſs'd in plainer <hi>Engliſh:</hi> Upon which they Rebelled in <hi>Devonſhire, Oxford, Buckingham, Norfolk,</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> to the great hazard of the unſettled Kingdom and Proteſtant Religion, then as young and weak as the Prince, who was Head of both.</p>
            <p>In the Reign of his Famous Siſter, and Succeſſor,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>W<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Churchill</hi>'s Div. Brit. p. 313.</note> Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> they played the ſame Part with her; for the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded by <hi>Aſtrological</hi> Predictions of her ſhort Reign, were eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drawn into many deſperate Conſpiracies againſt Her, to the great Peril of that Renowned Life and Government.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:93964:31"/>
            <p>How acceſſary they were to that grand Rebellion againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Martyr,</hi> to the great Detriment and eternal Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> as the Statue 12 <hi>Car.</hi> 2.30. moſt ſenſibly expreſſeth it, appeared by the Almanacks and other Fire-brand Libels, publiſhed and ſcattered about the Nation, by thoſe two great <hi>Incendiaries, Lilly</hi> and <hi>Culpeper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Reſtauration of his Son, they continued to Plot againſt the Government upon the ſame bottom: For if we may believe the Narratives of <hi>Dugdale</hi> and <hi>Smith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 26.</note> the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> having told the Jeſuits that King <hi>Charles</hi> would outlive his Brother, they reſolved to croſs the Stars, and cut him off, that the <hi>Duke</hi> might Succeed to effect their long projected Deſign, of introducing Popery; and hence ſprang that Plot, which cauſed ſo much noiſe and fear to this divided Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the late unhappy Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> ſhews how much he was ſeduced by this wicked Art, and inſtigated to that Rebellion which ruined him, and endangered the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of us all.</p>
            <p>How much the like Deſign hath been agitated ſince by the like Men, I have ſufficiently ſhown.<note place="margin">Tacit <hi>Ann.</hi> 12. lib. 2. Dion. <hi>in vit.</hi> Dom. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian</hi> de Offic. Proc. lib. 7. <hi>Sueton,</hi> lib. 9. <hi>C. Agrip.</hi> van. c. 31. Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> Eccl. Introd. p. 22.</note> Indeed in all <hi>Ages</hi> and moſt Nations they have been ſo pernicious to the common Wellfare, that as I have proved, they were often driven out of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> in the times of <hi>Tiberius, Vitellius, Conſtantine, Gratian, Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Juſtinian</hi> (as appears in his <hi>Code</hi>) made it a Crime Capital to Practiſe it. And <hi>Conſtantius</hi> (another Chriſtian Emperor of great Fame) as ſoon as He came to the Throne, made it loſs of Life to Conſult <hi>Aſtrologers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By our own Laws it hath been Fellony to Practiſe that Helliſh Art: And it's ſtill puniſhable by Fine, and Impriſonment. See 33 <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII. c. 8.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 15. And indeed conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fatal Experience we have had of thoſe vile Men, and their wicked Practices, the Tools they have been to the Factions, their notorious Cheats, how they have been forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by <hi>God</hi> himſelf, and exploded by Men of all Ages, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Faculties, it's a wonder they are permitted to live among us.</p>
            <p>To conclude: If <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> err in their Fundamentals, and are miſtaken in the firſt Elements of their <hi>Art:</hi> If the late diſcovery in <hi>Aſtronomy</hi> have given the Heavens a new Face, hid to the Inventors of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> and to all before this Age: If they differ among themſelves, have no Accord; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93964:32"/>and Prognoſticate contrary to one another, and to Truth: If the Preſages of the moſt Famous among them, commonly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> prove falſe, and contrary to Event: If they are ignorant of the moſt remarkable Occurrences in the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they happen; and of their own Fates, till they come to paſs: If Men of one <hi>Geneſis</hi> and <hi>Commencement,</hi> have various Fortunes, and multitudes of different <hi>Horoſcopes,</hi> one punctual Period: If the recurrence of Conſtellations <hi>do</hi> not again pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the ſame Men or Effects: If Cuſtoms and Circumſtances of whole Regions, continue unvaried under daily Changes in the Heavens: If multitudes of Men, learned even in <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> exclaim againſt it, as vain and wicked; and affront the Stars in ſpight of their Power; or rather in conformity to their Influence: If it be an Enemy to Providence and Free Will: If it advance Principles deſtructive of <hi>Religion,</hi> and promoting <hi>Idolatry,</hi> deſtroy <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and the force of natural Remedies: If <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> and their Art be no leſs pernicious to the Publick Welfare, are the Authors of Hereſie, and Rebellion, and as ſuch have been not only proſcrib'd by the wiſeſt Governments, but forbidden by <hi>Scripture,</hi> exploded by <hi>Fathers,</hi> eminent <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, States-men, Politicians, Philoſophers,</hi> and the moſt learned <hi>Wiſe Men</hi> which have been in the World; and by them all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a Cheat, and dangerous Impoſtors, we have cauſe enough to renounce it.</p>
            <p>I thought to have ended with this Summary,<note place="margin">See <hi>Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merbroek de pect.</hi> cap. 8.</note> but remembring that among the many trifling Arguments urged in behalf of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> and to prove the Influence of Heavenly, on Sublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Bodies, they urge one which they call manifeſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative, <hi>viz.</hi> the Power of the <hi>Moon</hi> on the Sea, cauſing the Flux and Reflux thereof by its preſſure,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tr. Phyſ.</hi> page 4.</note> as <hi>M. Rohault</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth it. I will ſhew this infallible Argument to be a <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Error,</hi> and that the <hi>Moon</hi> hath no more force to move the Waters, than the Waters have to move the <hi>Moon,</hi> or make it into a green Cheeſe; but that both are independant from each other. Their Motions indeed are concurrent in ſome few places of the World: But without relation, as Cauſe to Effect; or any Influence,<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Philips</hi>'s Letter to Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il. Tr. 34.</note> or Operation at all one on the other.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This ſeems manifeſt by all Tide Tables publiſhed Yearly by thoſe <hi>Almanack-Makers</hi> themſelves: For they tell you, That different degrees of Tides happen in places of this Nation, and parts adjacent at the ſame time: Now if the <hi>Moon</hi> move the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:93964:32"/>Water, let them tell us how a Full <hi>Moon</hi> makes high Water at one place, and half Tide at another, not far diſtant. If the <hi>Moon</hi> move the Water, ſurely it would make the Tides a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, or near ſo, at all places, eſpecially neighbouring ones, when it's in the ſame Age and Station: But the contrary is told us by themſelves: And there are others aſſure us, that in ſome places of the World, the higheſt Tides are at the Quadratures of the <hi>Moon,</hi> when it's loweſt with us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the <hi>Moon</hi> cauſe the ebbing and flowing, how comes the Sea to keep ſo regular and exact to the Laws of its Motion, when the <hi>Moon</hi> is in the other <hi>Hemiſphere,</hi> as when in this? To think that the <hi>Moon,</hi> which they ſay is cold, can operate through ſo remote, opaque, and bulky a Body as the Earth,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>More</hi> ubi ſupra, p. 339. 340, 345, 349, 353, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> when we are ſenſible that ſo piercing, and hot a Planet, as the <hi>Sun,</hi> cannot do it, ſeems the Opinion of a <hi>Lunatick,</hi> or an <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger,</hi> rather than a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> or Man of Sence.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>If the Moon,</hi> &amp;c. How is it that the Spring-Tides happen, as at <hi>Plimouth,</hi> two days after the <hi>New Moon,</hi> and as many after the Full? The Refraction of the Sun's Rays, which is ſuppoſed, cannot be the Cauſe; nor is it conſiſtent with any other of the many <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> by which the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> have been formerly ſolved.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>If the Moon be the Cauſe,</hi> &amp;c. How comes it, that there are not Tides (at leaſt regular ones) all the World over? For ſince the Cauſe is univerſal, one would expect the Effect ſhould be ſo too. But that failing gives us cauſe to ſuſpect we are miſtaken in imputing it to the <hi>Moon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> and thoſe Parts of <hi>America</hi> of our own Latitude, where the <hi>Moon encreaſeth,</hi> and wanes, riſeth, ſhines, and ſets exactly as with us, there is no regular motion of the Sea. What little ebbing and flowing there is, is moſt manifeſtly occaſioned by Winds, and Land-floods. So in <hi>Denmark</hi> and the <hi>Soundt,</hi> there are no Tides,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Molſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi>'s Account. <hi>p.</hi> 14.</note> but a ſmall Current of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters made by the Winds blowing in or out, as we are told by an obſerving Man, lately Reſident at <hi>Copenhagen.</hi> At the <hi>Cape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verd</hi> Iſlands, <hi>W. India</hi> Seas, and many other Places of the World, where <hi>Cynthia</hi> is as powerful as here,<note place="margin">P. 148. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ult.</hi>
               </note> ſhe hath no ſuch Operation, or Influence at all: Nor is there any diſcernible change in the Sea, Wind, or Weather. The <hi>Caſpian</hi> Sea, which is an hundred and twenty <hi>German</hi> Leagues long, and nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty broad, is ſalt as the Ocean, and hath multitudes of Rivers falling
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:93964:33"/>into it, but neither Ebbs nor Flows, as the <hi>Holſtein Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors</hi> obſerved in their Travels, <hi>p.</hi> 148.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>If the Moon,</hi> &amp;c. Whence is it that in ſo many Places of the World, the Current of the Sea runs always one way, and that ſo ſwiftly, as is ſcarce credible? From the Gulph of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rida,</hi> to the Latitude of forty degrees, it runs <hi>North-Eaſt</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred of Leagues. In the Streights of <hi>Gibralter,</hi> it runs alway ſo ſtrongly Eaſtward, as to force a Ship in againſt a fierce <hi>Levant</hi>-wind. In the <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tum Magellanicum,</hi> its force is ſuch, that no wind is ſtrong enough to carry a Ship againſt it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>If the Moon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heylin.</hi> Coſ. lib. 2. p. 615.</note> &amp;c. How is it that ſome very fierce ones are ſo irregular, variable, and uncertain? Like that of <hi>Euripus,</hi> which it's ſaid ſo puzled <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> to comprehend, that He threw himſelf into it.<note place="margin">Journal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Greece,</hi> p. 458.</note> 
               <hi>Si quidem ego non capio te, tu capias me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>George Wheeler</hi> tells us, that its prodigious ebbing and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hath been juſtly admired in all Ages for one of the greateſt Wonders in the World. He, Father <hi>Jaques, Paul Babin,</hi> and <hi>Ignatius Bradi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. Tr. <hi>71.</hi>
               </note> who viſited this wonderful Gulph, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, that it commonly flows 7, or 9 times in a day; ſome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> changeth its courſe 14 times in 24 hours. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in an hour and half change its Motion 3 times. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of a Month it moves ſo regularly, as to be red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> But in the other part of the Month, it's not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and changeth Motions from 7 to 14 times a day, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> all that motion, riſeth not above a Foot, ebbs toward the shore, and flows when its Motion ſeems ebbing towards the Sea.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the ſtrange, and ſurpriſing Appearances in this miraculous Gulph of <hi>Negropont,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſeudod. Ep.</hi> lib. 7. c. 14.</note> which Sir <hi>Tho. Bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to ſave <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Credit, endeavours to diminiſh: But my Authors who examined things on the Spot, relate with great ſurprize the amazing <hi>Phaenomena</hi> they ſaw there. And if there were nothing prodigious in it, it's notwithſtanding ſufficient to my purpoſe, to prove that ſome Motions of the Sea are <hi>Anomalous,</hi> and therefore not governed by ſuch a regular Cauſe, or Guide, as the Moon is; ſhe is conſtant to her Motions, the Sea is not, but in the compaſs of one Year, is in one, or other of its diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Circumſtances, at every hour of the Moon's Age. Be ſhe full, or new, increaſing or waning, the Sea of <hi>Euripus</hi> obſerves her not; but be full, or low, on this, or the contrary Motion, when the <hi>Moon</hi> is in every, or any of her Figures.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:93964:33"/>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>If the Moon,</hi> &amp;c. how is it, that in contrary Poſitions the ſame Effect is produced, as in <hi>Plimouth,</hi> a N. N. E. and W. S. W. <hi>Moon,</hi> make High-Water, and Spring-Tide alike, when at each time ſcarce above the <hi>Horizon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>If the Moon be the Cauſe of the Seas Flux and Reflux,</hi> by its Preſſure, Reflection, or Refraction; How is it poſſible that the Motion of the Sea ſhall run counter to that of the <hi>Moon?</hi> As it is on the Coaſt of <hi>Devon,</hi> and <hi>Cornwal;</hi> the ſtrongeſt Flood runs oppoſite to, and againſt the Face of the <hi>Moon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How abſurd is it to affirm, that a bright and dark <hi>Moon</hi> ſhall have the ſame Effect? That a Body fourteen times leſs than the Earth, and at ſuch a great diſtance from it, ſhall preſs the Ocean to ſuch an aſcent, and while it's in the like Situation, force it to retire; and this Influence to be in ſome Places only of the ſame Latitude, no more liable to it, than thoſe where it begets no ſuch Effect? That it ſhall move the Sea in this <hi>Hemiſphere,</hi> when it's in the other? That the motion of the Sea in ſome places ſhall be ever one way, in others irregular, in others conſtant to Rules of Flux and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux, and in ſome have no motion at all, in ſome move contrary to the motion of the <hi>Moon,</hi> and in others to all the degrees of Ebbing and Flowing at all times of the <hi>Moon</hi>'s Age? Theſe things plainly ſhow that <hi>Planet</hi> hath no Operation on that Element; and gives us reaſon to think that in thoſe few parts of the World, where their Motions conform to each other, it's from Concomitancy, Concurrence, or, as <hi>Iſaac Voſſius</hi> believes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Mot. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> cap. 16, 18.</note> from an accidental <hi>Synchroniſm,</hi> without Phyſical dependance; or according to ſome other of thoſe ways, by which Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Moderns have ſuppoſed it to be done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Galileo,</hi> and after him <hi>Gaſſendus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Aeſtu Mar.</note> aſcribe it to the great Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celeration and Retardation of the Earths Motion, compounded of the <hi>Annual</hi> and <hi>Diurnal,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>More</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">notes on <hi>Pſychatha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſia</hi> p. 391. <hi>Dial. Phyſ.</hi> p. 406.</note> The Flux and Reflux of the Sea depends on the Motion of the Earth, and attempts to demonſtrate it by divers Schemes of his own, <hi>Galileo</hi>'s, and <hi>des Chartes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Learned <hi>H. Fabri</hi> endeavours to ſolve it by the Preſſure of the <hi>Atmoſphere,</hi> and that the Tides vary according to the inequality, or the different Circles of the Air's Preſſure, and the ſeveral Tracts of thoſe Preſſures, in reſpect of their Situation and Extent.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:93964:34"/>
            <p>Our Famous Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Phil. Tr. 16.34.64. &amp;c.</note> That the whole difference of Tides, <hi>viz. Diurnal, Menſtrual,</hi> and <hi>Annual,</hi> and all the Motions of the Sea which concurr with the <hi>Moon,</hi> depend on one Common Cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the Common Center of the Earth and <hi>Moon</hi>'s gravity. This he endeavours to explain and prove, and anſwers all the Objections, and difficulties in, and againſt it. But as our <hi>Athenians</hi> ſay, If that were true, the many great Ponds of Water in <hi>England</hi> being thinner than the Sea, would have Tides in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. Des Cartes</hi> aſcribes it to the greater Preſſure made upon the Air by the <hi>Moon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Princip. Phil.</hi> Part 4. <hi>Myſt.</hi> p. 346. <hi>Phyſ. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan. Exp.</hi> p. 65.</note> and the intercurrent Aethereal Subſtances at certain times of the day, and <hi>Lunary</hi> Month, more than at others: But although Dr. <hi>More</hi> calls it a plain Solution of the Matter, Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> and Sir <hi>Chr. Wren</hi> ſuppoſe, if that were true, it would have the ſame effect on the Quickſilver in a long Tube.</p>
            <p>So that the Cauſe of this Motion ſeems as hidden, as that of the Heart, <hi>known only to him who made it.</hi> And the <hi>Athenians</hi> Opinion of it is the trueſt;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mere.</hi> Vol. 1.3. Vol. 8. c. 14.20 Vol. 9 c 8.</note> That <hi>the Sea moveth not by the</hi> Moon, <hi>but the neceſſary Law of the Creation, or the firſt eſtabliſhed Order of Nature, no more to be accounted for, than the Motion of the</hi> Sun, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And after all, if their Hypotheſis were true, and the <hi>Moon</hi> did move the Waters, it would not help them to prove the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the Stars on other Earthly Bodies, ſo many times farther from us, more than the Light given by a Candle in my Chamber, would prove that it did Illuminate the whole Hemiſphere.</p>
            <p>The only ſenſible Operation any Heavenly Body hath on us, is light and heat, and both from the <hi>Sun;</hi> and yet we ſee how gloomy and frigid the Air is, when he is removed but ſo far as beyond the <hi>Aequator,</hi> and how the Life of Vegetables, and ſome Animals ſeem then wholly dampt and extinguiſh'd. How much more would it be ſo, if he were ſo remote as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,</hi> and <hi>Jupiter?</hi> Now if becauſe the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> Operate ſenlibly on us, you will inferr, that thoſe remote and undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernible <hi>Planets</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> have Influence, of which we are not ſenſible; it is arguing from certainty, in behalf of uncertainty, which is no good <hi>Logick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another Inſtance which <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> give to prove the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Stars on Sublunary Bodies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gaſſend.</hi> c. 4.</note> is the <hi>Dog Star,</hi> which they
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93964:34"/>ſay is known <hi>to cauſe great heat;</hi> but I ſay it's no ſuch matter. It's true, that the time of his appearance happening in the fervour of the Summer <hi>Solſtice,</hi> in the Days of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (when it was firſt obſerved) gave occaſion to the Miſtake. But as now it appears a Month later than it did then, without any change in the Seaſon; ſo when Ten Thouſand Years hence (if the World laſt ſo long) it will riſe Five Months later, and by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the <hi>Equinoxes,</hi> his Kennel be as low as <hi>Capricorn;</hi> it will make no more alteration in it, but become then to us on this ſide the <hi>Aequator,</hi> what it is now to them ſo far on the other, <hi>viz. a Significator of Cold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Add to this, That if the <hi>Canicular Star</hi> cauſed the Heat of the <hi>Dog-Days,</hi> why do we not feel it in <hi>February,</hi> and in the Night, the <hi>Star</hi> being then above our <hi>Horizon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this, and much more which I might urge, proves that the ſuppoſed heat of it comes from the <hi>Sun,</hi> who having accended the Air in his way to our <hi>Tropick,</hi> in his return meeting this <hi>Star,</hi> the Old <hi>Aſtronomers</hi> falſly attributed that fervour to the <hi>Dog-Star,</hi> which is wholly owing to the <hi>Sun,</hi> and would be, if no ſuch <hi>Star</hi> appeared.</p>
            <p>For a third Argument in behalf of <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> we are ask'd a Queſtion ſit only for the Mouth of thoſe Men. What are the <hi>Stars</hi> made for, if not for <hi>Influence?</hi> By which they ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt that they are made for nothing elſe. But I will Anſwer them with another Queſtion; Is any Man now ſo Ignorant of the <hi>Coeleſtial Syſtem,</hi> as not to know that thoſe Millions of Stars viſible to us, beſide the many Millions more beyond our Ken, are <hi>Suns, Moons, Earths,</hi> habitable, and without doubt inhabit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Orbs,</hi> of vaſter Magnitude than this Earth? Or will any but an <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> believe, or ſuppoſe thoſe <hi>Myriads</hi> of vaſt Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were created to be the cauſe of Mens Vices, Miſeries, and Ruin; to force, or incline them to all their deteſtible Villai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; to be the Inſtruments of fatal neceſſity, and force poor Mortals to thoſe Actions, they would not otherwiſe be guilty of? Are <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> themſelves ignorant, that they give Light and Direction in the Night, and in Navigation tell the Mariner his <hi>Latitude,</hi> when the <hi>Sun</hi> is obſcured on the <hi>Meridian?</hi> Are they not reaſonable grounds to admire the Power of the <hi>Great Creator,</hi> and the Beauty of Heaven? Is not the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Regularity of their amazing Motions a great Conviction of <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> and a proof of the <hi>Deity?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:93964:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>John Gadbury,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Almanack</hi> 1692.</note> that Stale Bafled <hi>Advocate</hi> for <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> hath lately offered ſeveral other Ridiculous Things in defence of it, which the <hi>Athenian Philoſophers</hi> have ſufficiently Confuted and Expoſed, to which I referr <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> and without <hi>Aſtrology</hi> can foretel him, that ſo Ignorant and Unlearned as I am, I have ſaid more againſt his Art, than he is able to Anſwer.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:93964:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LPEPER REDIVIV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S:</hi> Or, a Second Part of <hi>SIDROPHEL VAPULANS:</hi> Briefly containing ſome ſhort <hi>Reflections</hi> on a late Scandalous Libel againſt the <hi>Royal College of Phyſicians, London;</hi> Entituled, <hi>A Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke,</hi> &amp;c. Written by <hi>William Salmon.</hi>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Ecce iterum Criſpinus.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Juven.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>TO prevent Amuſement, Sir, and help you to underſtand rightly (if it be poſſible) ſome Paſſages in the foregoing Epiſtle, it's needful to tell you, That it was written four Years ſince, and hath lain ſo long in Lavender, by Advice of ſome Friends, who thought <hi>Sidrophel</hi> ſo Contemptible a Block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, as not to be worth the Notice even of the meaneſt <hi>Artiſt;</hi> That his Railing was no more to be regarded than the barking of a Dog; That to oppoſe him would give him Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and be apt to make People think him Conſiderable, who is indeed a Contemptible Adverſary; That to meddle with him, would foul a Man's Fingers, raiſe Duſt in his Eyes, and Noiſe in his Ears; That Reaſon and Argument were loſt on ſuch an Incorrigible, and Conceited Opiniator; and would be ſo far from Silencing, or Amending, that it would Animate and Provoke him to greater Clamour and more noiſy Scolding.</p>
               <p>Theſe Diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſives have hitherto reſtrained me from taking the Satisfaction which hath been ſo long my due, and giving him the Chaſtiſement he hath ſo long deſerved: But when I ſaw in his laſt Scandalous Libel againſt the <hi>College,</hi> the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93964:36"/>Impudence with which he Affronts thoſe <hi>Worthies,</hi> and in what a Senſeleſs, Rude manner he Reproacheth ſo many Great and Learned Men, and that upon no other occaſion, but a moſt <hi>Pious and Charitable Deſign</hi> to relieve the Poor, when neglected and refuſed by others, who were Requeſted and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the <hi>College of Phyſicians</hi> and City, to engage in that Charitable Undertaking, I laid aſide all diverting Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to purſue that of a juſt Reſentment againſt ſo Shameleſs, and Scurrilous a Reviler: And accordingly reſolved that his Ignorance and ill Manners ſhould no longer be a Sanctuary to him, but that I would Expoſe and Puniſh him by the Pen, who hath ſo much offended with it.</p>
               <p>How Culpable and deſerving Chaſtiſement he is, his own Pen confeſs'd, while he was Railing in the midſt of his Dung-Boat againſt the <hi>College</hi> and the Author of <hi>Medicaſter Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus,</hi> and beſpattering us with his naſty <hi>Cargo;</hi> even then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ſtinking Diſpenſation, Rage and Malice ſo blinded and tranſported him,<note place="margin">Seplaſium Pref Sect 11.</note> that he forgot what he was doing, and declared, That to <hi>fling Dirt on any Man, was inhumane and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian;</hi> and yet no Man has been more buſie in that filthy Practice than he; and even againſt ſuch, to whom more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and Deference was due, than to an hundred ſuch as I am.</p>
               <p>In his laſt Libel againſt the <hi>College</hi> and its Worthy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers (which hath thus provoked me) he doth in moſt oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious Language (with great Impudence, and little Senſe) Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile their Perſons, Diſparage their Skill, Undervalue their Learning derogate, from that Power and Authority which divers <hi>Acts of Parliament</hi> and <hi>Royal Charters</hi> have given them; Reproaches and Cenſures their late Generous Project, to ſerve the Poor with <hi>Advice</hi> and <hi>Medicines</hi> without Profit; arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate a Power, and pretend an Ability to Reform <hi>Phyſick, Surgery, Pharmacy, Chymiſtry</hi> and <hi>Anatomy,</hi> &amp;c. and to make his new Houſe an <hi>Academy,</hi> and himſelf an <hi>Oracle,</hi> Greater, and Wiſer than <hi>Apollo.</hi> Wherefore, Not to Expoſe and Chaſtiſe ſuch an Inſolent and Vain glorious Aſſumer, were a fault equal to his own: I have therefore taken in Hand the Rod which hath ſo long lain in Pickle for him, and put it in ure, that this <hi>Noiſy Spark</hi> may better know himſelf, and the World ſee how Empty a Creature he is, who thus would Affront and Impoſe upon his Fooliſh and Ignorant Admirers.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:93964:36"/>
               <p>I ſuppoſe that Honourable and Learned Body, to which this ignorant Empirick is ſuch an Enemy, will not be wanting to Vindicate themſelves, and Puniſh him according to his Deſerts: Power and Ability I am ſure they want not; and I doubt not, but they will exerciſe both on ſo provoking an occaſion, and not ſuffer their Reputations and Intereſt to be ſo overborn, and trampled on by ſuch a Swiniſh Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, but ſtop the Career of his Brutiſh Pen, by ſuch means as Law and Learning have put into their Hands, in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of which, my Remarks on his Libel ſhall be the ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>There is lately Publiſhed by a free thinking <hi>Republican</hi> a <hi>Book,</hi> wherein, one whole Chapter is employed to prove,<note place="margin">Theol. <hi>and</hi> Polit. Diſc. <hi>cap.</hi> ult.</note> 
                  <hi>That Men under ſuch a Free Government as ours, ought to have the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thinking as they pleaſe, and writing what they think. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drophel</hi> ſeems by his Practice, to be of his Opinion, for he ſets no bounds to his Thoughts, nor limits to his Pen; but, like a true <hi>Libertine Libeller,</hi> lets both fly at all Games, mounting his filly Railery at the moſt Eminent for <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> in the Three Kingdoms, if not in the whole World.</p>
               <p>What it is that exaſperates him to this Barbarous Outrage againſt them, beſides the common Antipathy and natural En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of <hi>Ignorance</hi> to <hi>Art,</hi> and <hi>Empiriciſm</hi> to an <hi>Academick Education,</hi> I am to ſeek; unleſs his Soul be that of <hi>Culpeper Tranſmigrated.</hi> I find he Wheedles and Cajoles the <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> but that's like the <hi>Algerines</hi> putting out Chriſtian Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours to Delude and Captivate. His Compaſſion is feigned, and his Alarm falſe. He endeavours to make them believe the <hi>College</hi> deſign to ruin the greateſt part of the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> while he above any Man (except his Learned Friend <hi>G. H.</hi>) hath made it his buſineſs to deſtroy all that are in <hi>England.</hi> What the <hi>College</hi> did was in their Favour, to eaſe them of unprofitable <hi>Patients,</hi> and too many poor, miſerable and diſtreſſed Complainants, and gave good Reaſon for it. But his endeavours have been conſtant to deprive them of the Rich as well as Poor Cuſtomers, by teaching their Art to all, who can read <hi>Engliſh;</hi> directing and encouraging the People to make their own Medicines, Publiſhing Swarms of Receipts in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manacks and Popular Pamphlets, magnifying <hi>Noſtrums, Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nums;</hi> recommending Medicines, and crying up to Sale Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of his own ſilly Invention, Compoſition, and Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93964:37"/>which is the utmoſt any Man can do, to ruin their Trade. So that Maugre all his Soothing and Clawing, he is ſo far from being their Friend and Advocate (as he pretends) that he really is the moſt notorious, and moſt miſchievous <hi>Enemy</hi> they have in the World, next to <hi>Health.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How much then like a <hi>Crocodile</hi> is he, to lament the <hi>Chimeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> ruine of ſo many Families, to whom his own devouring Practice is deſtructive? And what a Sycophant is he, thus to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid the <hi>College,</hi> and accuſe them of a Wickedneſs he ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly commits, and hath ſo long Practiſed? If his Deſign be to engroſs that <hi>Pious</hi> Work of ruining ſo neceſſary a Trade, he had cauſe to be angry with them for medling in his Buſineſs, and taking Work out of his Hands; but then he ought in good Manners to have told them ſo.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>Surgeons,</hi> he likewiſe pays great Compliments, and makes high Court. The <hi>Maſter</hi> of the <hi>Hall</hi> he Dubs <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable,</hi> and makes them all better Men than the <hi>Doctors;</hi> gives their <hi>art</hi> the Preference both for <hi>Worth</hi> and <hi>Antiquity;</hi> and accounts a <hi>Surgeon</hi> ſo neceſſary to compleat a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> that he pronounces all ſuch as are not excellent in that Art, to be ignorant of the other.</p>
               <p>If this be the Only and True Character of a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> pray what is <hi>Sidrophel,</hi> who is neither <hi>Surgeon</hi> nor <hi>Apothecary,</hi> much leſs a <hi>Phyſician,</hi> but a Railing Fool, who is notoriouſly ignorant how mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h the <hi>Company</hi> of <hi>Surgeons</hi> have been obliged to the <hi>College</hi> of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> for their Improvement, even in their own Art; nor yet the Advantages which all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the <hi>College</hi> of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> do happily enjoy for their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement in <hi>Surgery:</hi> For it cannot be deny'd, but that the moſt conſiderable <hi>Anatomical</hi> Improvements made in our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, are chiefly owing to the Learned <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>College;</hi> ſuch as Dr. <hi>Harvey, Tern, Scarburgh, Croon,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo ſenſible the <hi>College</hi> hath been hereof, that they paſſed a Statute forbidding any of their <hi>Members</hi> to read any Publick Lectures, even in <hi>Surgeons-Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> unleſs the <hi>Maſter</hi> and <hi>Wardens</hi> did firſt ask the <hi>Preſident</hi>'s leave; giving this Reaſon in their Statute, <hi>Quippe aequum &amp; ratio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i conſentaneum arbitramur, ut qui per Collegam aliquem pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iunt, ii Collegio ipſi aliquod grati animi Officium praeſtant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I may be bold to ſay, That the <hi>College</hi> have ſo great. Advantages both as to <hi>Anatomical</hi> and <hi>Chirurgical</hi> Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93964:37"/>that no Society in <hi>Europe</hi> hath the like; there being no leſs than Three different Lectures founded in that <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Body:</hi> One a Fellows Lecture, whereby every Fellow, at his Admiſſion, is obliged publickly to Diſſect a Human Body at ſuch time as the Preſident ſhall appoint. A Second is a Lecture Founded by the Learned Dr. <hi>Coniſton, Anno</hi> 1635. which is to be read Yearly by one of the Four Youngeſt Doctors of the <hi>College,</hi> upon two, three, or more ſuch Diſeaſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as the <hi>Cenſors</hi> of the <hi>College</hi> ſhall Appoint or Direct. A Third (and the moſt conſiderable of all, both for Antiquity and Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs) is a <hi>Chirurgical Lecture</hi> founded in the 24th of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> by the Right Honourable <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Lumley</hi> and Dr. <hi>Caldwall,</hi> to reſtore Surgery to her Perfection, by procuring an <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Reader,</hi> who ſhall read openly in the Houſe of the <hi>College</hi> of the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> in good Order, all the whole Courſe of the <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Science</hi> of <hi>Surgery,</hi> which hath been moſt Learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed, not only as to the <hi>Anatomical,</hi> but <hi>Chirurgical</hi> Part of our <hi>Art,</hi> by thoſe Great and Learned Men, Dr. <hi>Foſter, Dun, Harvey, Scarburgh,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that <hi>Sidrophel</hi> hath little Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to charge them with Ignorance in our Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>And yet after all this Deference and Ceremony to the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons,</hi> he doth them alſo all the Miſchief he can, and ſtrives to Ruin them by the ſame Method he doth the <hi>Apothecaries;</hi> Teaching, as well as he is able, every Body to cure themſelves; but <hi>the Curſt Cow hath ſhort Horns:</hi> His Deſign of Proſtituting and Expoſing our <hi>Art</hi> to the Vulgar, doth us little harm; partly becauſe he is unable to teach it, but chiefly becauſe it's not to be Learnt by Words or Writing. <hi>Experience is our Maſter:</hi> And to that he is a Stranger, and ſo we become ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and ſafe from the Damage his Pen doth the <hi>Doctors, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>Chy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> eſpecially thoſe of the <hi>College,</hi> he behaves himſelf with the ſame Rudeneſs, and abominable Scurrility, <hi>Culpeper</hi> did before him. Some Paſſages I have Collected and Expoſed, which is Refutation enough; meer ſhewing ſuch a Monſter, being ſufficient to render him odious. I know none of his Dirt can ſtick upon Men ſo much above the reach of ſuch a Virulent, Malicious Rayler; although he labours hard with all imaginable Affronts, to provoke and abuſe them.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:93964:38"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Seplaſium. Ars Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurg. Rebuke.</note>Some times he charges them with <hi>Falſhood, Murther, and the Death of Thouſands;</hi> and makes the late <hi>Queen</hi> a Victim of their <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Male-Practice.</hi> Sometimes he prefers the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> as Men more uſeful, and having more Skill in Phyſick, and Advantages of learning it than they: And affirms, No Man can be a good Doctor, till he hath ſerved Fifteen Years with an Apothecary; as if cleaning Shops, Shooes, Streets, Skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and Glyſter-Bags, running of Errands, beating <hi>Diapente,</hi> and ringing <hi>Quevedo</hi>'s Paſſing-Bell, were of more uſe in Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Art of Phyſick, than Studying Books, Hearing Lectures, Viſiting Hoſpitals, and Converſing with Learned and Skilful. Men in the Univerſities.</p>
               <p>If ſo, I would ask this Pretender to the Skill and Title of a Doctor, with what Apothecary he ſerved his two Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticeſhips? If with any one of that Trade, he can pretend to no other Character by Law than his Maſter had. If with none, then by his own Confeſſion he hath not been duly Educated in Phyſick, and is unfit for the Practice of it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Billingſgate</hi> Language, the <hi>Bedlam</hi> Senſe of his Libel, is obvious to every Man of Manners and Underſtanding; the Vain-glorious Part of it, is no leſs palpable in the many oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions he takes to magnifie himſelf and vilify others: Boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Great Practice, Great Succeſs, Great Skill, Great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, a Great Houſe, and a Great Library; and all but a <hi>Great Nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Law Part, his Ignorance and Error are no leſs manifeſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Ch. Gooda's Vind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. <hi>cap 1. And his</hi> R. Coliege Founded by Law.</note> as a Learned Member of the <hi>College</hi> hath long ſince demonſtrated, and he will ſpeedily find to his Coſt, all his Objections againſt their Authority, and the Acts Eſtabliſhing it, are by that Worthy Perſon fully Anticipated and Confuted.</p>
               <p>If any Man of <hi>Puncto</hi> be ſo over n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce to think I Treat this Rude Adverſary two ſeverely, or uncivilly, and not like a Man of Breeding; I beg the Favour of him to conſider the Provocation which he hath given, not to me only, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to the <hi>Royal College</hi> and other his Superiors, whom he Ridicules, and Banters, Affronts and Reviles without any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to their Degree and Character. How much like an aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned Clown he Beſpatters them in divers of his Libels, and in one little Pamphlet, he doth over and over call them <hi>Lyars, Quacks, Empiricks, Knaves, Villains, Fools, Thieves, Robbers Scounderels, Pitiful Mean Fellows, Sneaking, Envious, Malicious'
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:93964:38"/>Ignorant, Iroud, Freſumptous, no Doctors</hi>— and then let him tell me, whether he Deſerves better uſage than I give him; or ought to be treated with Civility, who hath ſo Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated it, and like a <hi>Beaſt of Prey,</hi> forfeited all Right to Law.</p>
               <p>To conclude this loathſom Employment: I have read a great many Libels with which the Liberty of late Times hath Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd the Nation, but in none found ſuch a mixture of <hi>Brutiſh Ignorance, Sawcy Rudeneſs,</hi> and <hi>a want of Senſe,</hi> or <hi>Truth</hi> as in this; many Falſe and Dangerous Things have been ſet off with a good Grace, and Cloathed in an Eloquent Civil Stile, with an Air or Semblance of Reaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But in this we meet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like it. No Manners, Senſe, Wit, Learning, Truth or Reaſon; but down-right Ribaldry, Slander, Falſhood, Folly, and Rudeneſs, as I will ſhortly make evident, if not prevented by ſome more Concerned, and better able to Vindicate the Learned <hi>College,</hi> and Expoſe this Odious, Clamorous Witling, than</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J.Y.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>December</hi> 2. 1698.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
